<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God wooing his church: set foorth in three godly sermons. / By William Burton preacher at Reading.</title>
            <author>Burton, William, d. 1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07428</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 76698297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4174.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91261</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">76698297</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 76698297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184215</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07428)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184215)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 2240:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God wooing his church: set foorth in three godly sermons. / By William Burton preacher at Reading.</title>
                  <author>Burton, William, d. 1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 148 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by V.S. for Iohn Hardie dwelling in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Tygers head.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border; headpieces (McK. 303); printer's device; initials.</note>
                  <note>Head-piece; initial letters.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁸ K².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped; tightly bound; print show-through with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in: Peterborough Cathedral.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184215:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184215:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>God wooing his Church:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Set foorth in three godly Sermons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By William Burton preacher at Reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>V.S.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Hardie dwelling in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> at the ſigne of the Tygers head, 1596</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:184215:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184215:2"/>
            <head>God wooing his Church. The first Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREMIE Chap. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 14</hi>
                     </bibl> O ye diſobedient children, turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſaith the Lord, for I am your Lord, and I will take you one of a citie, and two of a tribe, and will bring you to Zion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 15</hi>
                     </bibl> And I will giue you Paſtors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mine heart, which ſhall feede you with knowledge and vnderſtanding.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe wordes be part of an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation begunne in the 12. verſe of this chap. and made to the captiue Iſraelits in Aſsiria, in the 9. yere of <hi>Hoſhea</hi> king of the ten tribes, as appeareth in 2. <hi>King.</hi> 17.6. And it groweth vppon a complaint againſt Iuda, becauſe that Iuda did not profit by the iugements of God vpon Iſrael: which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint being ended, the Lord here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the prophet to labor with the ten tribes that were in captiuitie, that they might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite better by thoſe afflictions which were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184215:3"/>vpon them, and by timely and hearty repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to turn vnto God, which if they would yeeld vnto, the Lord doth alſo promiſe for his part to forget all their ſinnes paſt, and to place them in their former eſtate of libertie againe.</p>
            <p>This Scripture hath two partes; an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, and a Promiſe. In the Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there are two circumſtances to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of: the firſt is of the perſons; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is of the matter ſubiect. The perſons be two-folde, exhorted, and exhorting: the perſons exhorted are the captiue Iewes deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed in the twoo firſt wordes, <hi>diſobedient children.</hi> The perſons exhorting are alſo double, the Lord by <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the name of the Lord; and that appeares in theſe wordes <hi>[ſaith the Lord.]</hi> The matter ſubiect is two-folde; firſt, what it is that they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted vnto, in theſe wordes, <hi>Turne againe:</hi> ſecondly, a reaſon why, in theſe wordes, <hi>For I am your Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the manner of ſpeaking to the perſons exhorted, doth notably appeare the ſingular wiſedome, and vnſpeakeable mercy of God. Gods wiſedome appeareth in ripping vppe of their ſinnes, before he exhorteth them to repentance: Yea that he may bring them to repentance for their ſinnes; he ſaith not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, O my children, turne againe, leſt they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184215:3"/>ſhould take an action againſt <hi>Ieremy,</hi> for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching their credit: but he ſaith, <hi>O ye diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient children,</hi> that ſo hee might conuince their conſciences, ſtop their mouthes, and take away all occaſion of boaſting. From this wiſe courſe of wiſedome it ſelfe, in calling men to God, both the miniſter of God, and euery chriſtian brother may learne this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable leſſon; that the readieſt way to bring men from their profaneneſſe to true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, is firſt to conuince them of ſinne, and then to exhort them to repentance. Many cry repent, and amend, thundering out the iudgements of God againſt the people: this ought to be done; but if we do not firſt ſhew them what is amis, they wil ſay as the proud Iewes ſaid to <hi>Malachie, What haue wee done?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.13, 14</note> But let <hi>Malachie</hi> tell them what their words are, and then they wil bluſh for ſhame. Then will <hi>Felix</hi> tremble,
<note place="margin">Act. 24.26.</note> when <hi>Paul</hi> preacheth of righteouſnes, temperance, and iudgement to come, all which do concerne him. Then will <hi>Dauid</hi> confes his ſin,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.7.</note> when <hi>Nathan</hi> ſhall lay the parable cloſe to his conſcience. Then is <hi>Nabal</hi> ſtriken as a ſtone,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when <hi>Abigaile</hi> ſhal wiſely watch hir time, and tell him of his churliſhnes.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.19.</note> Then will the Samaritane wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man leaue hir ſcoffing, when Chriſt ſhall come home to her conſcience. Then wil the ten tribes returne (if euer they will returne)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184215:4"/>when <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſhal ſummon them before gods iudgement ſeat for diſobedience. And then may the Preacher look to profit by his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like doctrine; and the brother by his priuate counſell, when firſt they ſhal proue to their conſciences, that of this and that ſin they are guilty.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from this wiſedome of God, we learne that it is lawfull and neceſſary for the miniſter of god ſomtime to vſe ſharp words, if he meane to do any good, ſpecially when he hath to deale with men whoſe faces are of braſſe, whoſe necks are of yron, whoſe harts are offlint, and whoſe conſciences are ſeared vp with an hote iron. And yet he is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to lay on loade, but ſometime (with <hi>Paule</hi>) to doubt whether hee ſhould come with a rod, or with the ſpirit of mildneſſe; &amp; as he ſhall perceiue them either obſtinate, or tractable, ſo to make the edge of his repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion blunt, or ſharp; as he ſeeth his Stil to drop, ſo to quicken or ſlake his fire; and ſo to ſtraine, or let downe the ſtrings, as that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by too much ſtraining, or too much looſening, they be brought more out of tune then they were before.</p>
            <p>Againe he is not to handle all alike, but to remember that as all the ſtrings, of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument are not alike placed, alike natured, alike ſounded, nor all ſtrained alike, nor all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184215:4"/>out of tune alike, and that according to their place, quantitie, and qualitie, euery one muſt more or leſſe bee ſtrained, ſo it muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men. The magiſtrate is to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but with great reuerence, and ſingular modeſtie. The miniſter is to be reproued,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1.</note> but as an Elder. The elder ſort muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued, but as fathers. The yoonger ſort muſt be reprooued, but as children. And euery one according to his place and calling muſt be dealt withall.</p>
            <p>Againe, if two be fallen into one and the ſame ſinne, he is wiſely to obſerue how they came down, &amp; warily to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the one and the other. The one may fall by weakeneſſe, the other of wilfulnes, the one of ignorance, the other of mallice: the one therfore with lenity, the other with ſeueritie muſt be proceeded againſt, alwaies tempering his ſpeeches according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and diſpoſitions of perſons with whom he hath to deale, and according to the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and quantitie of the ſinne againſt which he dealeth: examples hereof we haue not a few in the ſcripture.
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.20. Pſa. 2 9.</note> Chriſt will not breake the bruſed reede, nor quench the ſmoking flaxe, but the rebellious hee will batter in peeces, like a potters veſſell.
<note place="margin">Num. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was the meekeſt man on earth, yet none more angry with <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.6.</note> nor more ſeuere againſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184215:5"/>then he.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 26.28.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> will perſwade <hi>Felix</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a chriſtian,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4, 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.11.14.</note> and will conuey himſelfe into the bowels of the Gallatians to winne them to Chriſt, but hee meaneth to take vp <hi>Peter</hi> for halting,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 113.10.</note> and to pronounce <hi>Elimas</hi> the verie child of the deuill.</p>
            <p>As this doctrine was alwayes profitable, ſo neuer more needefull then now, when there be <hi>quot homines tot ſententiae,</hi> how many men, ſo many minds. Some would haue the preacher ſpeake alwaies alike, and that of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but of mercy and ſaluation, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of new wine and ſtrong drinke, but in no caſe to awake them out of their ſins. Som would haue him alwaies to bee thundering out the iudgements of God, and to miniſter nothing but bitter purgations, as though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll men were ſicke at once, or of one diſeaſe, or of one cauſe. Some againe can abide neither piping, nor mourning. If the miniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue their ſinnes, they call him a buſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolour: If he ſhall applie the word to the conſcience, then, who made him a iudge? If he denounce the iudgements of god, then he fraieth his audience. If he ſtandeth aboue his houre, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is tedious. If he entreat friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then he is glad to curry fauor. If he be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in reprofe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is afraid to diſpleaſe. If he ſpeake learnedly, then he is too deepe. If plainely, then he is no ſcholler, but if he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184215:5"/>will ſooth them vp with an <hi>Omne bene,</hi> or a <hi>nihil dicit,</hi> then he is the beſt church man that euer they knew.</p>
            <p>Thirdly the Prophet telleth the Iewes of their diſobedience, that ſo hee might make them more fit to returne vnto God, being firſt humbled with the ſight of their ſinnes, to teach vs, that in all our reprehenſions or admonitions, we muſt ſeek the good of our brother, and the glory of God; as <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt called the Phariſes and Sadduces a generation of vipers,
<note place="margin">Mat. 3.7</note> not to make them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate, but fruitful in the workes of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And ſurely (good brethren) then is there hope of doing good by ſharpe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, when men may ſee that they are not cenſured of malice, or to make them odious, or for ſome other ſiniſter reſpect, but of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and loue, ſeeking therby the good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of our brother, and that we are no whit glad for their faults, but rather grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at their falles. And if this rule were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies obſerued, amongſt all thoſe to whome the cenſures of the church are committed, I doe not doubt but that much more good might be done, then is done; but if men ſhall ſee that their cenſures (whatſoeuer they are) proceede not from a hatred of ſinne, nor a conſcience and care to amend their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but either of ſtomack to reuenge their own
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184215:6"/>quarrelles, or from a couetous affection, to maintaine their own gaines; alas, how ſhould they be regarded as they ought? Nay, howe ſhoulde the kingdome of Sathan bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, when the golden iudge giueth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence? Howe can the right marke bee hit, when a wrong marke is ſet vppe to bee ſhot at?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.9.</note> and howe can the Church bee terrible as an armie with banners, when the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the army ſhall turne their ſwords points againſt their owne ſouldiers but this may ſuffiſe for the wiſedone of God in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning their ſinnes, before hee calleth them to repentance, in this firſt word <hi>diſobedient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the firſt word is a moſt euident teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Gods wiſedome, ſo is the ſecond of his mercie; for lo, he calleth them ſtill by the names of children. Oh loue vnſpeakeable, that cannot ſo forget the workemanſhip of his owne hands, but albeit they had moſt ſhamefully abuſed his maieſtie, yet ſtill offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be their father. He ceaſeth not to try them by afflictions, to call them by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to draw them by his ſpirit, to wooe them by his benefits, to pardon them in his mercie,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 103.9.</note> and to receiue them into his wonted fauour againe. Thus wee ſee that our God will not alwaies be chiding, neither will hee keepe his anger for euer, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> but as a father pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth his children, ſo hath the Lord compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184215:6"/>on all thoſe of whoſe returne there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hope.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicat. </seg>
               </label> This doctrine will ſtand vs in ſtead many waies; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt the papiſt may learne from hence, that the Lord doth not deale with vs, according to our deſerts, but according to his merits in Ieſus Chriſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly from hence the afflicted conſcience (that groneth vnder the burden of his ſinnes) may fetch comfort againſt al the firy darts of Sathan, when hee ſhalbe ſurely perſwaded that in Ieſus Chriſt the partition wall is broken downe, and the hand-writing faſtened vnto his croſſe, and therefore, that al his ſinnes ſhall not be able to ramper vp the gate of Gods mercie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Thirdly this teacheth vs, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that if any be fallen by infirmitie, wee ſhoulde doe what wee can (with the ſpirit of brotherly loue, &amp; long ſuffering) to reſtore him again. And good reaſon, for if we be bound by the law of God to helpe vp a beaſt vnder his burden, much more our brother; but alas, how ſtrange is this amongſt vs? If a mans foote hath ſlipped neuer ſo little, eſpecially if hee be a good man (and who can ſay his heart is cleane?) profane men are ready to exclaime of him, but neuer labor to reclaim him; neuer remembring what our ſauiour Chriſt ſaid when he wrote vpon the ground,
<note place="margin">Iob. 8.7</note> but forgetting themſelues to be laden both with moats, and beames, they do as dogs do,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184215:7"/>which (when one is in diſgrace) run al toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after him with open mouth and ful cry. Now if the Lord ſhuld thus hotly purſue vs, as we do our brethren, what ſhould become of vs? Fourthly, this gracious example of our heauenly father, dealing ſo mercifully with his diſobedient children, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demneth the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable practiſes of three ſorts of men: the firſt ſort is the Papiſts, whoſe fingers are dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a ſanguine colour in the bloud of thoſe men, which haue but tranſgreſſed the dirtie decrees of an Italian prieſt; &amp; yet theſe gnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainers, and camel ſwalowers, bewaile the want of loue among vs: ſecondly it meeteth with an abuſe in church gouernours, who vſe ſometime to make out exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications for fees, for trifles, and matters of ſmall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as though the greateſt cenſure of the church and the greateſt iudgement next to the generall iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may be dallied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and ſo farre abuſed, as thereby to cut off, &amp; caſt out members of the church, to ſathan at mens pleaſures. Our good God caſteth not off his people, no not for diſobedience, but ſtill admoniſheth them, and taketh them for his children, ſo long as there is any hope of returning: thirdly it meeteth with the raſh &amp; furious dealing of Browniſts, who (for ſom defects and blemiſhes) caſt off the whole church of God in England for no apparant
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184215:7"/>church of God, which is more then they ought to do for two cauſes. Firſt, thogh diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience be (as it is indeed) as the ſin of wich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, and who is not diſobedient in many things? yet ſo long as they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not chalenge vs, for apoſtacy, as we may ſome of them, and ſo long as there is any life of the ſpirit at all in her, ſhe is not to be laied out vpon the colde ground. But ſoft a while: though ſhee hath not all her ornaments according to the word of God, yet ſhe doth not refuſe them, if ſhe might lawfully come by them; but is readie to receiue them whenſoeuer ſhee may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obtaine them.
<note place="margin">Ezech. 9.4</note> In the meane time ſhee mourneth for her wantes, and ſeeketh a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe as ſhe may, and ſueth as ſhe ought, and therefore no doubt is marked on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head for the deare ſpouſe of Ieſus Chriſt, ſo long as ſhee holdeth the foundation in him. But ſuppoſe that the church of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d were proued as the church of Rome, a very har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, and were adiudged for her continuance worthy to be put into the black book of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, (which God forbid) yet for them to be their owne caruers and bailifes, is more then they ought,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4</note> being but priuate men: and this is certaine, that no particular congregation, much leſſe a priuate perſon may excommunicate a whole church.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, in ioyning theſe two words toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184215:8"/>wee are taught to cenſure ſinne in all men, but yet to iudge charitably of all. And on the other ſide to iudge charitably of all, but ſo as we winke not at ſin in any,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 19.17.</note> for that were to hate our brother. And this are wee taught here, while God calleth them diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient; yet ſtill children: and children, but yet diſobedient. Many thinke that wee hate them if we tell them of their ſinnes, taking thoſe for their beſt friends, which do alwaies ſooth them vp in their ſinnes, but theſe men are much deceiued;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 7.6.</note> for the reproofe of a friend is better then the kiſſe of a flatterer; yea, if <hi>Shimei</hi> an enemie ſhall raile vpon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> though that bee <hi>Shimei</hi> his ſinne, yet it may be and ought to be <hi>Dauids</hi> benefit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the ſweeteſt words to the eare, are not alwaies the wholeſomeſt to the heart: no, the bitter pill is better to purge, then the ſweete perfume. The boiſterous wind will make a man hold his garment faſt about him, when the gleaming ſunne will make him put off al to his ſhirt. The thunder and lightning doe more purifie the aire, then the calmeſt day in ſummer. The greeneſt herbe doth often couer the fouleſt toad, where the water is ſtilleſt, there is it deepeſt; the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt garment doth often couer the filthieſt carkas; when the baite is moſt in ſight, the hooke is leaſt ſuſpected; the friendlieſt kiſſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184215:8"/>in ſhew, is ſometime but treaſon in ſubſtance; the Bee hath hir honey, ſo hath ſhe a ſting, and the one ſhal wound more then the other ſhall heale; when <hi>Herodes</hi> courtiers ſhal crie to <hi>Herod,</hi> Oh the voice of God, not of man, then muſt <hi>Herod</hi> come downe with a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; when 400. falſe prophets ſhall ſay to <hi>Achab,</hi> go and proſper, then muſt <hi>Achab</hi> looke leaſt to thriue, neither ſhal he returne in peace: and ſo much for the perſons exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in theſe words, <hi>O ye diſobedient children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The perſons exhorting are, God by <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and the prophet in the name of the Lord, and this is of force alſo to enforce the exhortation: as if he ſhould ſay, I doe not of my ſelfe thus reproue you, for then you might thinke me too buſie, but the Lord ſet me aworke, whoſe will I muſt obey, and therfore you muſt heare me with patience. Thus <hi>Ieremy</hi> pleadeth his commiſsion, partly for his owne diſcharge, and partly to make his meſſage of more credit and force with them. And thus might <hi>Ieremy</hi> reaſon. He that is but a ſeruant, muſt do his maſters meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: I am but a ſeruant, therefore I muſt do my maſters meſſage. And againe, he that doth but his maſters meſſage, ought not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be blamed; I do that, and no more, and therefore I ought not for that to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And againe, whatſoeuer the Lord by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184215:9"/>his meſſenger ſaith, that muſt be beleeued: but the Lord (by me his meſſenger) ſaith that you are diſobedient, &amp; promiſeth that if you wil turne againe, and obey him, he wil be your Lord, therefore you muſt beleeue it. And againe, whatſoeuer the Lord by his meſſengers doth command, that muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beied; but the Lord by me doth commaund you to turne againe, therefore ſee that you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his commandement as you will anſwere at your vtmoſt perill. Here then we haue three things to conſider of in the miniſters of God: Firſt their authoritie, ſecondly their dignitie, thirdly their dutie.</p>
            <p>Their authoritie is very great,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>titie.</note> and their commiſſion is very large; for behold (ſaith the Lord to <hi>Ieremy</hi>) <hi>I haue ſet thee ouer nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and kingdomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.10.</note> 
               <hi>to plucke vp, and to root out, to deſtroy, and to throw downe to build and to plant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2</note> But how? <hi>Exechiel</hi> ſheweth how; <hi>Thou ſonne of man, feare them not, nor their wordes, although thou remaine among ſcorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, feare not their lookes, for they are a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious houſe;</hi> verſe 7. Therefore thou ſhalt ſpeake my words vnto them: ſo that it muſt be done without feare, and by ſpeaking the word of God without ceaſing. The miniſter of the word therefore hath authoritie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue princes,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 36.15 27.2.</note> as the prophet ſaith, but not by the ſword to remoue princes as the pope
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184215:9"/>ſaith.
<note place="margin">Iob. 20.23.</note> He hath authoritie in Chriſts ſtead to pronounce forgiueneſſe of ſinnes to the faithful as the Euangeliſt ſaith, but not to abſolue whom he liſt as the pope ſaith. He hath authoritie to reproue things amiſſe in the church, or the common weale by doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine as the word ſaith, but not of himſelfe to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orme by practiſe, as Browniſts ſaie, for depoſition of Princes belongs to God only: forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, belongeth to God only: reformation of churches and common weales belongeth to Princes onely, but the reprouing of ſin in prince, church, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth belongeth to miniſters alſo. And this in wiſedome and diſcretion, they may &amp; ought to do. Nay bloud for bloud, if they do leſſe then this, if they do more then this, and if they do not all this; Why then ſhould <hi>Moſes</hi> be murmured at? why ſhuld <hi>Michea</hi> be ſmitten? or why ſhould <hi>Ieremy</hi> be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? and al thus troubled for executing their commiſsion? haue they not authoritie to ſpeake? Nay we ſay to you, (if you be angrie with vs for this) as your ſeruants will ſay for themſelues. We are but ſeruants, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to vs, agree with our maſter and wee ſhallbe content, wee may ſpeake what his word ſpeaketh, for we haue authoritie, and ſo much we muſt ſpeake, for the refore are we put in authoritie. And ſo much briefly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184215:10"/>for the authoritie of Gods miniſters.</p>
            <p>As their authoritie is great, ſo is their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling excellent, and honourable, in reſpect of their office, and of his perſon, whoſe mouth they are. We can thinke as baſely of our ſelues, as any can either think or ſpeak of vs, but if it be an excellent thing to bee a kings ambaſſadour, howe much more then to be embaſſadour to the king of heauen &amp; earth? Therfore are they called in the ſcripture by names of great account;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.15.18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.12.</note> as <hi>Angels, Stars, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Horſemen, and Chariots of Iſrael,</hi> wherof ſome be old as <hi>Heli</hi> was, ſome be young as <hi>Timothie</hi> was, yet all the meſsengers of the Lord Ieſus.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 22.3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 25.15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 20.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 9.17</note> Some haue tenne talents, ſome haue but one, yet all muſt occupie for their Lords aduantage. Some come at the firſt houre, ſome at the laſt, yet all ſent of God. Some are like <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſonnes of thunder,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.7. Cor. 4.1.</note> ſome like <hi>Barnabas</hi> the ſonne of conſolation, yet all the meſsengers of God. Some haue receiued a greater meaſure of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fts, ſome a leſſe, yet all according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt. And therfore let vs eſteeme of them as of the miniſters of Chriſt, and the diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God. Men they are as we are, that is our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, for if God himſelfe ſhould ſend forth his voice, we muſt yeeld vp our liues. Sinfull they are as others,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that is, becauſe they are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184215:10"/>men, mortall they are as others are, and that is becauſe they are ſinfull; yet ſtill the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of God, and beſeech vs in Chriſt his ſtead to be reconciled vnto God.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> If this were regarded, then Gods miniſters ſhoulde be more regarded, and leſſe deſpiſed, more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, leſſe diſgraced, better prouided for, leſſe pinched, and not ſo ſhamefully ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and abuſed of ſo many as now they are. But alas, it is not once thought vpon of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and therefore euerie churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> denieth them maintenaunce, euerie coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous <hi>Achab</hi> is ſicke for their liuings,
<note place="margin">1. King. 21.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> euery proud minion, and minſiing damſell longeth for their heads in a platter,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.15. 1. King. 22.4</note> euerie <hi>Iudas</hi> is ready to betray them <hi>Zidkijah</hi> the kings claw backe will not ſticke to take his fiſt from their cheekes,
<note place="margin">Act. 24.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullus</hi> the oratour dareth call them peſtilent fellowes, and troublers of the ſtate, if any man of his courteſie will giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hearing. <hi>Feſtus</hi> in his mad mood,
<note place="margin">Act. 26.24.</note> will call them mad men, and lay the fault (if there be any) vpon their learning too.
<note place="margin">2. Tim 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Demas</hi> the wordling will giue them the ſlip,
<note place="margin">1 King. 17 9.</note> onely the poore widdow of Sarepta is founde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing poore baniſhed <hi>Eliah.</hi> And ſome (thanks be to God) but not many in reſpect of the multitude, haue the ambaſſadours of the Lord Ieſus, in that good account which they ſhould, eſpecially for their works ſake,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184215:11"/>for do not many grudge our meate, number our morſels, and reckon our liuings to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry farthing? Chriſt commanded his to carry neither bread nor money,
<note place="margin">1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor to put on two coates: he is a rich man nowadayes that hath two coates to put on, except ſome that haue twoo or three benefices, for many in the world are turned out of all, and yet (God be thanked) they are deliuered. We may ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaide, we are afflicted on euery ſide, in pouerty,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4.8.</note> yet not ouercome of pouerty; as dead, yet aliue; as ſorrowing, yet reioycing; as poſſeſsing nothing, yet hauing all things. In the time of popery one congregation did maintaine many maſſe-prieſts, now many congregations will hardely maintaine one good preacher of the goſpel: and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for then there were too many fooliſh Bees that brought all their honny into the popes hiue, and nowe wee haue too many droanes that ſucke all the hony out of the churches hiue; yea too many horſe-leaches, which alwaies cry,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 30.15.</note> Giue, giue, but neuer ſay, Ho. One crieth, giue me the college landes, another crieth, and mee the landes of cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall churches; another longeth for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations; the fourth muſt haue an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther benefice or two for to buy him bookes withall; one is ſicke for a deanry; and ſome are ſicke of a conſumption, and a biſhoprike
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184215:11"/>or twoo would reſtore them againe, or ſome other thing that ſhould go to the church, and ſome will not leaue till they haue the deuill and all, or till the deuill haue them. If men take paines, ſome will rewarde them with a thiſtle the reward of an Aſſe: others would ſend away their paſtours in worſe caſe then the baſeſt officer in their kitchin, without either warning or wages. I blame not all, but all ſuch. Why, ſay ſome of theſe men, can you not liue as the apoſtles liued? Why, ſay I againe,
<note place="margin">Act. 4.35. Act. 4.2.</note> let them lay downe their goods at the Apoſtles feete, and then let them aske that queſtion. Truely many dee as <hi>Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> did, if they giue one groat, they will brag of two. Many aske, from whence commeth the fall of the church? Indeede it is a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be moued, though the diſeaſe wil hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or neuer be remoued: It is ſaid that ſeuen ilfauoured leane kine deuoured ſeuen fatte kine, and this was <hi>Pharaoes</hi> dreame;
<note place="margin">Gen. 41.10.</note> but now ſeuenty times ſeuen ilfauoured leane kine haue deuoured ſeauen hundred fatte kine; and this is no dreame, but a very troth: but wherefore I pray you are Gods meſſengers thus handled? Doe they demaunde their dueties? No they dare not; for the earthen potte dareth not ſtriue againſt the braſen veſſell, and menne are nowe like drunken gueſts, which hauing filled their bellies are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184215:12"/>loath to pay their reckoning. What is the cauſe? Any cauſe will ſerue the turne in this point. <hi>Facile inuenias baculum, quo canem ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</hi> It is an eaſie matter to find a ſtaffe to beate a dogge withall. When the Phariſies could not abide the doctrine of Chriſt nor his diſciples,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 24.</note> they quickly found a iuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their quarrell. They do that on the ſabboth daie which is not lawfull. And wot you what that was; they plucked the eares of corne. Our Phariſes alſo haue taken vp the ſame accuſation againſt vs, for (ſay they) we do that on the ſaboth day that is not lawful. And firſt to begin withal, they crie, out vpon him rebell, he wil not weare the ſurplis eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſunday and holy day. Againe, he will not reade all ſeruice at all times, and therefore (whether lawe diſpence with him or no for his preaching we haue found ſufficient cauſe to denie him his dutie. Againe, he will not reade diuine ſeruice to the walles and the windowes: to the ſtooles and the ſtones, &amp; is not this cauſe ſufficient to denie him his dutie? Againe, they preach againſt papiſts, Atheiſts. vſurers, drunkards, ſwearers, lords of miſſc-rule, abuſe of apparrell, and other profanings of the ſabboth day, and ſuch like comendable, and common excerciſes of good neighbourhood, and is not this a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cauſe alſo? Laſtly, if they ſhould pay the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184215:12"/>miniſter his dutie, the lone of ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney were loſt, which in many yeares would amount to ſome round ſumme, and are not all theſe, or any of theſe ſufficient cauſes thinke you, to handle Gods poore miniſters and ſeruaunts as hath beene ſhewed before? But what hath good queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> done, that ſhe can get nothing of ſome of them, I hope it is not becauſe ſhe hath baniſhed ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and brought in the goſpel. Some can rob <hi>Peter</hi> to pay <hi>Paul,</hi> (they ſay) but theſe men can cunningly rob both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> too, and pay neither of both. Well, we haue beene all this while but among the eares of corne: but what? Are wee ſharpe in reproouing their ſinne? No, wee dare not ſay to <hi>Herod,</hi> thou muſt not haue thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife, wee may not ſay, that a right papiſt is a ranke traitour, leſt wee ſhould be told, that when we are in our priuileged places, wee prate what we liſt, as once I was tolde.
<note place="margin">Nehem. 13.17.</note> We may not ſay the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are profaners of the ſabboth day, if they ſuffer it to bee profaned, though the word ſaith ſo. And to meddle with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny abuſes or corruptions in the church, is <hi>Auribus canem,</hi> to pull a dogge by the eares, and to put our hande into a hornets neſt. A learned father (who belike had experience of ſuch things) ſaid once (if not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184215:13"/>often) <hi>Tutior eſt diſcentis, quàm docentis ratio:</hi> It is better to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earne then to teach: but wee may ſay nowadayes, <hi>Tutior eſt peccantis, quàm arguen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is conditio,</hi> It is more daungerous to reprooue ſinne, then to commit ſinne. And if euer it were true, it is now true, that <hi>Lepores concionantur leonibus,</hi> we muſt preach in fear as poore hates before proude lions: for if we pleaſe them not,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 22.8.</note> they will ſay as <hi>Achab</hi> ſaid, Hee doth not prophecie good vnto me, but euill, and therefore my ſoule doth hate him. We reade that <hi>Pharao</hi> cried againſt the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites as appeareth in <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Giue them no more ſtraw but let them gather it themſelues, and get it where they can, and yet we will haue our whole tale of bricke; And why ſo? for they be idle and crie, Let vs go three daies iourny in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wilderneſse and offer ſacrifice vnto God.</hi> So play many with vs, for they crie, let our paſtors and preachers haue no more liberty giuen them let them gather their ſtraw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that is, let them preach as much as they will (for they account of preaching but as offſtraw;) but in the meaue time we wil haue our whole tale of bricke, that is, all our old cuſtomes and ceremonies kept whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be: and albeit we haue no lawe for them, yet will wee haue them to doe as wee will. And why ſo? Becauſe for ſooth (as they ſay) we be idle, and crie, let vs go offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184215:13"/>that is (ſay they) they neuer leaue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to church, and to the ſermon euery day, and there wee muſt be reprooued for euerie fault, and this diet is not for our humors; and they were as good be idle as thus occupied. And as <hi>Pharao</hi> vrged thoſe things at Iſraels hands, which hee would not touch himſelfe with his leaſt finger: ſo theſe <hi>Pharaos</hi> would lay heauier burthens vppon the miniſters backes, then either prince, or lawe, or conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience will warrant. Againe, becauſe the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian taske was not done, the Iſraelites, and their officers were beaten. Euen ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their taske (I meane not the taske of the lawe, for that haue wee borne, and are ready moſt willingly to vnder go it) but the vnſtinted taske of mens vnbrideled affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe behauiour ſauoureth of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of an alehouſe, becauſe their taske is not done: we are beaten with the ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tongues of vngodly men, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch of the world, with the diſgrace of our miniſtery, with the bitings of pouertie; and if ſome might preuaile, with the loſſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, liuing, and life it ſelfe; for they crie <hi>Crucifige</hi> already, the Lord (if it be his will) turne ſuch <hi>Pharaoes</hi> hearts. But, will not the Lord be reuenged of his ſeruants wrong and oppreſsion? Yes no doubt; for if Princes take that contempt to themſelues which is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184215:14"/>offered to their ambaſſadours, much more will God.
<note place="margin">10.19.4.</note> If <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> ſtincke in the noſtrels of Iſrael, for their villanie offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Dauids</hi> meſſengers, much more ſhall theſe ſtinke before God. And if God made Ieruſalem, yea euen famous Ieruſalem a heape of ſtones, and the ſhame of the world, for mocking, deſpiſing, &amp; miſuſing of Gods meſſengers, how ſhall God ſuffer theſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing <hi>Pharaoes,</hi> whether they be papiſts, or atheiſts, or libertines, or neuters, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiauils, whether in city or country, whether in village or in cotage, or wherſoeuer or who ſoeuer they be, how ſhal God ſuffer them at laſt thogh he ſuffer them long to eſcape his heauy wrath? Therefore I would wiſh that this contempt and neglect of Gods mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters might be baniſhed from amongſt vs; for although in reſpect of humane infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they are but as other men are; although the meſſenger of Sathan bee ſent to buffet them; and though there bee a lawe in their members, rebelling againſt the law of their minds, whereby many times they are led (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wils captiues to the law of ſinne, oh wretched men that we are: yet in reſpect of their office which is honourable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in reſpect of him whoſe meſſage they bring; and in reſpect of the meſſage it ſelfe which they bring, they are to be regarded
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184215:14"/>and reuerenced: and ſo much for the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gods miniſters.</p>
            <p>Their authoritie is great,
<note place="margin">Of their dueti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> honourable is their office, and great is their dignity; their duety therefore muſt needes be very great, but which is the greateſt I know not. They are meſſengers of Gods counſelles,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.27. 1. Cor. 4.15.</note> therefore they muſt be truſty; they are fathers vnto Gods children, therefore they muſt be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and tender;
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10. 1. Cor. 4.2.</note> they are builders of Gods church, ſtewards of Gods houſholde, ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards of Gods flocke, therefore they muſt be skilfull, faithfull, and watchfull; they are captaines ouer Gods church,
<note place="margin">Cant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which is terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as an army with banners, therefore they muſt not be feareful and faint-hearted;
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.14.</note> they are the lightes of the world, and the ſalt of the earth, and therefore they muſt neither ſtand vnder a buſhel, nor be vnſauoury; they are nurſes of gods tender ones, therfore their breaſts ſhould neuer be without milke; they are to heale with old and yong, with learned and vnlearned, with ſtrong and weake, with wilful and ignorant, and with all ſorts, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt be wiſe. In the time of peace, and in the time of warre, in time of proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in time of aduerſity, in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, and at all times;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.12.</note> therfore they muſt be no time-ſeruers: Againſt principallities and powers, againſt holds mighty and ſtrong
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184215:15"/>againſt fleſh and bloud the world &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, the deuill and hell, preſumption and deſpaire, and againſt all ſin in others and in themſelues: before princes and ſubtects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore angels &amp; men, before heauen and earth, and before God himſelfe, &amp; therefore their garners muſt be ſtored with al kind of grain, both old and new, their lips muſt alwaies preſerue knowledge.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.52. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 17.12.</note> Their hands muſt be holden vp, &amp; their armes vnderſet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they faint in prayer, their eies ſhould dazle with waiting for the hope of their praier, their cheekes ſhuld be watered with teares, when they pray for the ſins of the people,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</note> &amp; when they can pray and preach no longer, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chatter like a ſwallow, mourne like a doue und grone in their ſpirites: for <hi>oportet Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum mori concionantem &amp; orantem,</hi> ſaith a godly father. A good Biſhop muſt die prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and praying, &amp; muſt pray and preach till he die. What ſhould I ſay more, he is the miniſter of God, therefore of God hee muſt learne his duty, and vnto God he muſt performe his dutie. Hee is to ſpeake in the name of god, therefore he muſt ſpeake both what, &amp; when, &amp; to whom, &amp; in that maner that God will. If therefore we ſpeake mens inuentions in painted eloquence to ſet forth our ſelues, to ſome &amp; not to all, faintly and coldly, to <hi>Tharſis</hi> for Niniuy, if we condemne
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184215:15"/>the good, and commend the bad, encourage the wicked, and diſcourage the godly, if we ſpeake but ance a yeare, once a quarter, or when we liſt, or not at all, and at all times as occaſion ſerueth, both inſtantly and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we doe not the dutie of good meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. But if wee ſpeake Gods glorious will, without adding or diminiſhing, in the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the ſpirit, to the conſcience as wel as to the eare, to the courtier and countrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, with courage and boldneſſe, with wiſedome and diſcretion, with a zeale of Gods glorie, a loue of Gods people, and a deſire of their good, and that continually, conſtantly, and faithfully, then wee doe the dutie of Gods miniſters, If therefore any man ſhal ſend for Gods miniſter, to ſchoole him before hande, and to teach him either what to ſpeake, as generall doctrine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out application, or howe to ſpeake, as in fine tearmes, and filed phraſes, to pleaſe all, and to diſpleaſe none (as the manner of ſome is, and who is not cunning in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters office, and in euerie mans office ſauing his owne) wee are to ſignifie thus much vnto him, that wee are not mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of mens vnbrideled affections, but of the Lordes moſt holie will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt not ſpeake either what they will, or how they liſt, but all muſt bee both
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184215:16"/>for matter, and maner as God wil; ſo ſaid <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah</hi> the tru prophet to the kings eunuch;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 23.3.</note> ſo ſaid <hi>Balaam</hi> the falſe prophet to the King himſelfe; and ſo ſay we to euery one. And good reaſon; for if the Lawyer wil ſcorne to learne of the Diuine to pleade at the barre, why ſhould the Lawyer take vppon him to teach the Diuine how to ſpeake in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit? And if our ſeruants are not to doe our buſines by other mens directions; if the ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward muſt not diſpoſe of his maſters goodes at another mans appointment; if the captain muſt not fight when the meane ſouldier wil appoint him; and if the ſouldier muſt not fight with ſuch weapons as his ennemie will appoint him, why then ſhould Gods miniſter (who is to pleade Gods matters, to doe Gods buſines, to diſpoſe of Gods trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and to fight the Lords battels) become a ſlaue and a ſeruant to mens affections? If he ſhould (which God forbid) hurt he may do much; but God he ſhal do none. And yet I deny not,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em. 23.32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.17.</note> but that the miniſter is to receiue good counſel of any man. And the Coloſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may ſay to <hi>Archippus,</hi> looke to thy mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. And ſo much for the authoritie, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and duetie of Gods miniſters. And thus much both for the perſons exhorted, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond part we are to conſider; firſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184215:16"/>of that whereunto they are exhorted, and then of the reaſon why. For the firſt, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and is here called a turning again: alluding to one that is out of his way, and cannot come into the right way, except hee turne againe, or elſe to one that had left ſome thing behinde him, without which his iourney could, not proſper, but moſt likely to a wife diuorſed from her husband,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 3.1, 8.</note> for adulterie, but he calling to mind the old and ſweet loue that was wont to be between them, calleth her againe, and offers ſtil to be her ſpouſe, vpon condition that ſhee wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a new woman. At all theſe ſtaies were we all of our ſelues, for by nature we are all gone out of the way, we are corrupt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come abhominable, the waies of peace we haue not knowen. But then did the Lord cal vnto vs, and ſaid, <hi>Adam where art thou?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.9.</note> come into the right way, Chriſt Ieſus the ſeed of the woman, is the way the truth and the life, walke thou in this way, and he ſhall conduct thee directly vnto Chanaan the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Againe, when we had found Chriſt the way, wee made no more reckoning but thought that we had all, when wee had the way, but we were denied; for we left behind vs the works of faith, and repentance. We were going to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Matt. 8.11.</note> not like the wiſemen
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184215:17"/>with our preſents, but like the fooliſh vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins without oyle in our lamps;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 25.</note> but behold, the Lord calleth vnto vs, and ſaith. Turne againe, and take your prouiſion with you, we alſo went a whoring after our owne inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 106.</note> we were trudging to hell, with bagge, and baggage, we had plighted our troth to the world, ſinne, and Sathan. Yet lo: God of his infinite mercie and goodneſſe, ſendeth embaſſadours after vs, his Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and miniſters, to call vs backe againe, and to offer vs condicions of peace. Nay hee ſent his owne ſonne to call vs backe againe, and he crieth,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 11.</note> Come vnto me, come vnto me, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c. 18.31</note> Nay God himſelfe calleth vnto vs, and he crieth vnto vs why wil you die, O houſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> why wil you die? when this would not ſerue, he falleth to entreating of vs, that we would be reconciled vnto him.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or. 5.20.</note> Oh loue without compariſon. Thus hath our good God, and moſt gracious father forbidde the banes of matrimonie betweene the deuil and vs,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r. 1.2.</note> and offereth vs a better match, euen his owne ſonne, the heire of all things and king of heauen and earth, and all vpon this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we will turne againe, and forſake the deuill, with all his works, and embrace Chriſt Ieſus with all his merites, and ſerue him in righteousnes, and true holyne all the daies of our life,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> bleſſed be his name for euer.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:184215:17"/>
            <p> Well then, by this time wee ſee what true repentance is, namely a continuall turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto God,
<note place="margin">Pro. 24.16.</note> by forſaking our old waies of iniquitie, and tranſgreſſion, and walking in the new waies of holy life,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.12</note> by caſting off the worke of darkenes, and putting on the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of light. This turning againe,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.11</note> is a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of all ſinne paſt, with a hearty ſorow for the ſame, with a care to preuent ſin to come, and a ſtedfaſt reſolution not to entertaine it, when it is offered againe.
<note place="margin">Act. 10.33.</note> It is a conqueſt of our owne wills and affections,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.7.</note> and a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting them vnto the will of God. The time of this turning againe muſt be alwaies, euen while it is ſaide to day. This turning againe muſt be by one certain way,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.</note> and that is Ieſus Chriſt. And for the better finding out of our way, &amp; keeping of it being found,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.5.</note> we muſt needs haue a lanterne to our feete, and a light to our pathes, and that muſt bee the word of God, read, preached, heard,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 1.8.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued and meditated vpon. And becauſe we walke in this world as on a ſea of glaſſe,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 4.6.</note> verie ſlipperie, and we verie feeble &amp; faint, wee muſt haue the ſtaffe of faith to goe by. Our guide muſt be the ſpirit of wiſedome, knowledge, vnderſtanding, of courage,
<note place="margin">Eſa. 11.2.</note> and ſtrength. And becauſe Chriſt our way is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ground, wee muſt therefore put off the ſhooes of our beaſtly affections, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184215:18"/>vs euerie way before, and put vpon our feete the ſhooes of preparation to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.15.</note> In this our turning again, we ſhal meet with many diſcouragements, we muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be couered with a helmet of hope, and leſt our old enimies the world, the fleſh, and the deuill, ſhould make vs retire backe, we muſt put vpon vs the whole armour of god,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.13.</note> be valiant, and quit our ſelues like men, and ſo march forward toward our heuenly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan. And if at any time we chance to looſe our way, as being either benighted, weather beaten, or otherwiſe beguiled, we muſt goe about the cittie; by the ſtreets and open pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.7.</note> and enquire of the watchmen, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that are ſet to go about the cittie, if they did not ſee him whome our ſoule lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at 5.3</note> &amp; if they ſhall ſhew vs where he is, we muſt not ſay, I haue put off my coate, howe ſhall I put it on? but leauing all ſuch dilatory pleaes, turne againe, and meete him with great ioy.</p>
            <p>If theſe be the properties and qualities of true repentance, then are many in the world far from true repentance.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>apiſts.</note> The papiſts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence with murther &amp; treſon. The price of whordome, inceſt, ſodomitry, patricide, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricide, fratricide, &amp; of all ſin is ſet down in the market of Rome where. <hi>Omnia venalia,</hi> al is for mony, &amp; the deuil clarke of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184215:18"/>far inough therefore are they from true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, neither can they be ſaued, except they turne againe. Their fooliſh penance of whipping, creeping to the croſſe, going bare foote, and ſuch like, God neuer required, and therefore no true conuerſion, except they leaue theſe toies and turne againe. The Turke followeth his Alcaron,
<note place="margin">Turkes.</note> euen darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe, leauing the word of God, euen light it ſelfe, and therfore ſo long as he doth ſo he cannot turne againe.
<note place="margin">Iewes.</note> The Iewes denied Chriſt the right way, and therefore they are farre from this turning againe.
<note place="margin">Anabap.</note> The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt reiecteth the written word of God, and relieth vppon his drouſie dreames, and night-reuilations, and therfote ſhal not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly find the right way, except he turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. The Neuter is for any way,
<note place="margin">Neuters.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of the right way, except he turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.
<note place="margin">Atheiſts.</note> The Atheiſt ſaith in his heart there is no god. The Machiuel with the Atheiſt, wil not acknowledge that there is either god or deuill, hell or heauen, and in all their actions they quench the ſpirit of god, which one day they ſhal know to their coſt, except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. The prophane worldling,
<note place="margin">Worldlings</note> with <hi>Eſau</hi> weepeth not for his ſins, but for the loſſe of ſom worldly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity,
<note place="margin">Preſumptuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but this is no true tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning. The preſumptuous perſon driues of al to the laſt hour, &amp; therfore is like to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184215:19"/>if in time hee doe not turne againe. The deſperate perſon is in hatred with himſelfe for his ſinnes,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ite.</note> but becauſe he wanteth Chriſt the way, and the ſtaffe of faith he layeth vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands vpon his owne body, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroieth the good creature of God, and ſo turneth further from god, then euer before. The turning turner that turneth with the weathercocke in the wind,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>coatrs.</note> muſt alſo turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine before he can be ſaued. The church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>papiſt turneth in ſhew,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> papiſt.</note> but not in truth, and therefore muſt looke for his portion with hypocrites except hee turne againe. The Barbarians turned from one opinion to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.4.6.</note> but both in extremities; for one while they iudged <hi>Paul</hi> as a murtherer, another while they eſteemed him as a God. Our Browniſts alſo once accounted highly of gods miniſters,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>niſts.</note> but now they account them but murtherers, and falſe prophets; once they thought our church to be the onely church, but now no church; but I hope that ſo many of them as belong vnto God, ſhall one day turne againe. Some turne from popery, to Atheiſme, from one ſinne to another, but to God they cannot turne, except by true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance they turne againe. Some turne as dogges do, that is, either to their vomit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or elſe to ſnatch at them which bring them meate. I would I could deuiſe a way
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184215:19"/>to make vſurers turne againe, but I feare mee I ſhall not, for they which can coſin al lawes, (no doubt) will be too cunning for me. Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is a deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that all the diſciples of Chriſt, in England cannot caſt out, for it is a kinde that will not be caſt out, but by faſting and prayer.
<note place="margin">Mar. 5.3.4</note> We reade that there was a man poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with a deuill called Legion, hee kept amongſt the graues, and no man could paſſe quietly by him: I thinke vſurers alſo are poſſeſſed with the ſame deuill, for no man can paſſe by without his marks. The father crieth, oh my ſonne is vndone by the vſurer, the ſonne crieth, oh the vſurer hath eaten vp my father, and euerie one that commeth that way where the vſurer keepeth, crieth, God keepe me out of the vſurers hands. No ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, nor lawes can tame vſurie, for he hath ſo many turnings and turne againes, that a man cannot tell where to find him. He is in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and wares, in buying and ſelling, he dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for ready money, and for time, hee bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth and lendeth, he dealeth by himſelfe and his brokers, the deuils huntſmen. And this is certaine, that vſurie is growe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſtrong, that hee hath ſinewes and bones like a man, and walketh vp and downe the ſtreetes like a ſeruing man, like a gentleman, like a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant man, and like an alderman; yea and that ſo ſtoutly that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e taketh the wall of all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184215:20"/>honeſtie and religion.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 31</note> Theſe turners are like the deuill, who being driuen out of a man, woulde needes bee in the ſwine, but whereſoeuer they be, they wil be ſure to do no good. Good brethren, in many things we ſin all, and therefore wee haue neede at all times to be turning againe. In euerie tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againe there is <hi>terminus à quo, &amp; termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ad quem;</hi> that is, the thing from which, and the thing vnto which wee muſt turne. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth that we muſt turn from idols,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> to the liuing God. And <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the firſt words of his text, ſheweth that we muſt turne from our diſobedience to true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for the reprouing of the one is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing of the other, and the forbidding of the one is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding of the other. And to ſay the truth, they are truely turned vnto God, who are truely obedient to the word of God, and they are indeed diſobedient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which diſobey the word of God. And therfore let vs make what ſhewes of holines we can if wee obey not the word in al things that concerne vs, we are vnholy, wee are not truely conuerted. The word of God forbids vs to follow the faſhions of the world,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.3</note> it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids men the wearing of long haire, &amp; wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the laying out of their haire, &amp; both men &amp; women to diſguiſe themſelues in ſtrange at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, now if (al this notwithſtanding) we ſhal
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184215:20"/>practiſe the contrary, what doe wee elſe but turne from the Lord vnto Sathan, who is our <hi>terminus ad quem.</hi> The Lord in his word for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids all lying, and falſe dealing to deceiue, and all deceit to liue; if any man in his ſhop, or elſe-where ſhall vſe both, they may well be hearers of the worde, but God will note them for monſtrous rebels and hypocrites. And thus wee are to examine our ſelues for euery other thing. For the wickedeſt man that liueth may heare the word of god glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reuerence the preacher,
<note place="margin">Mar. 6.</note> &amp; in many things obey the word, as <hi>Herod</hi> did; but <hi>Herod</hi> would ſtil haue his brothers wife, and ſo many will loue one ſin or other as their dearling. And ſurely the deuill can draw a man to hell aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well with one bait as with a thouſand. Gods children muſt therefore ſtriue againſt all ſinne, and in euery thing labour to obey the word; or elſe, as God did allowe the good things, and euer had ſomewhat to ſay for the euill that hee found in the ſeauen Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Aſia,
<note place="margin">Apoc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo will his maieſtie reckon with vs for all our ſinnes, not onelie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion but commiſsion; although he doe finde ſome, yea many good things amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>Many, vnder pretence of obedience to Princes would giue entertainement to any religion, forgetting that god muſt be obeied
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184215:21"/>before men, but ſuch men are moſt diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the King of al kings, but truely obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to none. Many againe crie, obedience, obedience, as though they were compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of nothing but of obedience, and yet all is not gold that ſhineth; and flattering <hi>Iudas</hi> is not the faithfulleſt diſciple; &amp; <hi>ex vnguibus leonem, ex fructibus arborem,</hi> the lyon ſhall be knowen by his clawes, and the tree by his fruit. For let a man looke well vpon many of them, and he ſhall ſee that there are not any generally to all lawes more diſobedient, in their liues, none more diſſolute and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in their worſhipping of god, none more ſuperſtitious, in the principles of true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, none more ignorant, in their dealing, none more vniuſt, and deceitfull where ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage is giuen them, none more cruell &amp; mercileſſe, and in all their ſports &amp; paſtimes none more profane, and filthy, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous; which kinde of people are not much vnlike <hi>Caius Gracchus,</hi> who tooke vpon him the defence of the treaſurie, wherof he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was the ſpoiler. So they crie obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when none are more diſobedient then they; like theeues which hauing done a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, can make hew and crie after the true man. Some can hold one with a tale, while they picke his purſe, but theſe are cunning theeues, which can hold the world with a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184215:21"/>tale of obedience, and conformitie, while they in the meane time doe deceiue both Prince, church, and common wealth of their duties, and themſelues of Gods fauour, if in time they take not a new courſe. Such hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hearted Ambo-dexters, haue learned to ſerue the time, but to ſerue their own turne, looking when time will turne, that they may turne with time: but if carefull circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection be had, which the neceſſity of theſe times requireth &amp; the ſubtilties of theſe eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies craue, it will be no hard matter to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the wolues, though they wander in ſheepes clothing, by the noiſe of their how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and to deſcrie the aſſe (though he iet in the lions ſkin) by the length of his eares, except by true repentance in time they turne againe, which God grant if it be his will.</p>
            <p>But heere ariſeth a queſtion, and that is this: Whether a man in turning to God, muſt forſake the companie of the wicked or no? If yea (as they ought indeede) why did theſe Iewes continue ſtill among the Aſſiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans which were idolatours? and why went they not to Zion, the place of gods worſhip? Of if they could not, becauſe they were in captiuitie, to what purpoſe then ſerued this exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The anſwer is not heard? There is a turning in outward action and affection: In outward action, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a chriſtian doth that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184215:22"/>which he ought to do, and may lawfully, &amp; conueniently do it. In affection when a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian would doe that which hee ought to do, but ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not, being letted outwardly, by impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, ſickenes, baniſhment, the lawe, or ſuch like: or inwardly by ſome natural infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. Examples we haue of both in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 19.7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 137.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> They turned in outward action, who with <hi>Dauid</hi> fetched home the arke, ſo did the Niniuites which faſted &amp; praied at the kings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement; ſo did likewiſe the Iewes and Grecians, which burned their books. In affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction turned the Iewes in Babilon, which mourned &amp; wept at the remembrance of Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In affection turned <hi>Dauid</hi> in baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deſired to go to Gods houſe with the people,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.4</note> but could not. In affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo turned thoſe men which mourned for all the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations that were done in the midſt of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem: And in affection alſo the Apoſtle turned,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 7.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deſired to do al that he ought to do, but could not, being led captiue to the law of ſin. So we in many things may turne, both in outward action &amp; affection of heart, as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idolatry to the goſpel, from drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes to ſobriety, from pride to humilitie, and in many things more. Som things are yet wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (which the church ſhuld haue, if ſhe had her right) as a learned miniſter through the whole land, and the prefection of that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184215:22"/>and ancient diſcipline, which was in the primitiue church, but as yet we cannot haue them in acte, yet in affection we embrace them that is, we pray for them, we woulde gladly haue them if wee might lawfully come by them, and this church doth allow in our booke of common prayer, where in plaine words it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Preface before Commination on Aſhwedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</note> 
               <hi>That there was a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcipline in the primitiue church, which is to be wiſhed; and much to be wiſhed, that is might be reſtored againe;</hi> and therefore alſo when occaſion ſerueth it may be taught, and yet with great wiſedome and diſcretion: for ſhall it be prayed for, and not be taught al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what it is, that it may be much wiſhed for? yes ſurely, for <hi>Ignoti nulla cupido,</hi> there is no deſire of that is not knowen. And in affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that which is wanting, we are to beware that impatient raſhnes draw out our affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions beyond the bond of chriſtian charity, and godly ſobriety, leſt we forget to bee thankeful for thoſe ſingular benefits which wee haue already receiued, and ſo for our impatience on the one ſide, and our ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude on the other, we are rewarded, in the ende with the loſſe of al.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the reaſon of the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in theſe words: <hi>For I am your Lord.</hi> The word Lord, in the originall ſignifieth to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund as a Lord, or to rule as a huſband:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:184215:23"/>either is ſufficient, ſo the ſence be taken, as if hee ſhould ſay; it is good reaſon thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt turne againe, for thou haſt entred a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant with me, and married thy ſelfe vnto me, and therefore I haue both power our you, and intereſt in you. This beeing the ſenſe, the doctrine ſhall be this; firſt, that it is neuer in vaine to turne to the Lorde, for ſuch is his loue vnto thoſe, whoſe names are once written in his booke of election, that finally he will not forſake them, but moſt mercifully will embrace them, whenſoeuer they ſhall faithfully turne vnto him: Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he ſhew vs this fauour becauſe we haue deſerued it by our turning againe, as the papiſts ſay, but becauſe of his free &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued loue hath made vs this promiſe. If any ſhal thinke that of himſelfe he hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer or will to turne vnto God, he deceiueth himſelfe; for by nature we run from God as <hi>Adam</hi> did,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 51.10.</note> but it is God that ſeeketh vs vp againe. Naturally our thoughts are euill continually, our wordes are vaine, our works are filthy; but it is God that createth in vs new hearts, and that makes our words graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 3.5.</note> and our works acceptable to himſelfe, &amp; that by Ieſus Chriſt for of our ſelues we can not ſo much as thinke a good thought.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ilip. 2.13.</note> And as God only by his grace preuenteth vs, and worketh in vs both the will and the deed,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 6.44.</note> ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184215:23"/>by the ſame ſpirit he draweth vs to him, or els we neuer come at him: and by no other ſpirit, doth he alſo finiſh that good work he hath begun in vs, &amp; that in Ieſus Chriſt. And as our repentance is of god, ſo is our faith al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; for S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Philip. 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>To you it is giuen both to beleeue &amp; ſuffer.</hi> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.65.</note> 
               <hi>It is the work of God to beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And what haue we that we haue not receiued? If we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued al the good we haue from god, &amp; not from our ſelues, and that of his free grace and mercy, without any conſideration of our parts, why ſhould we not attribute al to him again? &amp; why ſhould any part of our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or ſaluation be aſcribed to our ſelues, or any creature elſe in heauen or earth, and not wholy to the merits of Chriſt his death and paſsion?
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.17, 18, 19</note> for ſhall the diſobedience of one man, <hi>Adam,</hi> deſtroy all the world, and ſhal not the obedience of one man, Ieſus Chriſt, ſaue al that beleeue? ſhal the work of men, of Saints, of martires, or of <hi>Mary</hi> (all ſinfull and imperfect) be ſufficient, and not the workes of Chriſt Ieſus which are moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and perfection it ſelfe? Is he the ſeed of the woman that brake the ſerpents head, and could he not do it without vs? Is he that bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen ſerpent that heales all thoſe that look on him with the eie of a liuely faith, &amp; muſt we now licke our ſelues whole. But (ſay the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts)
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:184215:24"/>there is righteouſneſſe in vs as the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident in the ſubiect. To which we anſwer, firſt, though this be true in philoſophie, yet it is falſe in diuinity,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>loſſ. 2.8.</note> and therfore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Take heede leſt any man ſpoile you through phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie.</hi> Secondly, there is righteouſnes in vs, as ther was ſin in Chriſt; but in Chriſt there was no ſin really, of his owne, but of ours by imputation; neither haue we any righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our owne, but of Chriſts, and that by imputation alſo. Thirdly, God by his good ſpirit beginneth righteouſnes in vs, euen in this life, but it is imperfect and polluted, ſo ſoon as it commeth into the ſtinking veſſels of our corrupted nature,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. 64.6.</note> but it ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the world to come, by Ieſus Chriſt only. But yet the papiſts haue another ſhift, as our euill workes are auaileable vnto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, ſo our good workes are auailea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſaluation: for (ſay they) <hi>Contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum contraria eſtratio,</hi> of contraries, there is a contrary reaſon. But I anſwer, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is vnlike, and holdeth not; for firſt, our ſins are of our ſelues, our righteouſnes is of God: ſecondly, our ſinnes are perfectly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, our good is imperfect: thirdly, he that is guiltie of one commaundement is guiltie of all,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 2.10.</note> and deſerueth damnation; ſhall we ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude, that he which keepeth one, de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerueth ſaluation? what more abſurd? No, no,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184215:24"/>both our conuerſion and ſaluation bee the free workes of God.
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.14. Luke 12.31</note> Heauen is our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; <hi>ergo,</hi> no purchaſe by vs: it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Father to giue vs the kingdom; <hi>ergo,</hi> we get it not by our ſelues. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, Chriſt is the dore by which we muſt enter.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.7. Act. 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, there is no other name vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen whereby we can be ſaued, but onely by the name of the Lorde Ieſus. And therefore to ioyne Chriſt with vs, and his perfect righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, with our broken workes, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holineſſe it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Matt. 9.16, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> were but to put new cloth in an old garment, and ſo to make the rent worſe; and to put new wine into old bottles, and ſo to ſpill all; and to build part of the houſe vpon Chriſt, and part vpon our ſelues were to ſet part vpon the foundation,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.11.</note> and part beſides the foundation, and ſo to bring all vnder foote. And therefore if we will be wiſe builders, let vs aſcribe all wholy, and onely to our good God, who hath ſo loued vs in Chriſt Ieſus, that albeit we haue beene diſobedient to his heuenly maieſty, yet if we wil come when he calleth, and vſe the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary means when he offreth them, &amp; turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to him with al our hearts, he will be ſtil our Lord, &amp; that for his promis ſake in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, and yet al of his fauor vnde ſerued, and loue vnſpeakable, wherwithal he loued vs before the foundation of the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:184215:25"/>
            <p> This doctrine is neceſſary for two ſorts of men; Firſt, for thoſe that are too much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with the burthen of their ſinne, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to deſpaire: theſe men are to know that Chriſt Ieſus ſpake vnto them, when as hee ſaide,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 11.28.</note> Come vnto mee all you that are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy laden, and I will eaſe you. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet heere ſpeaketh vnto them, when hee ſaith; <hi>O you diſobedient children turne againe, for I am your Lord.</hi> Let them onely beleeue, and pray the Lord to helpe their vnbeleefe.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 9.24.</note> And let not this be the queſtion, whether God will be their good Lord or no; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall be ſaued or no; but whether they bee ſurely perſwaded of Gods loue in Chriſt to them or no.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.38.</note> The ſecond ſort are ſuch as are not at all touched with their ſins, but are drenched in the ſea of ſin, and feele not the waues; in the middeſt of the fire they are, and yet feele not the flame; Gods iugements are preſent, hell gates are gaping, and death ready to ſtrike them, yet they no whit abaſhed: No threatning, no promiſe, no example, nothing will make them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go their ſinnes, that God may forgiue them: God make vs to feele our ſins, that we may by true repentance turne againe; for this comfort belongeth to none but to thoſe that in obedience turne to God by Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:184215:25"/>
            <p> The ſecond thing that we learn from this place, is, that the conſideration of gods loue towards vs, ſhould moue vs to ſerue him in true obedience. This argument did <hi>Moſes</hi> vſe to the Iſraelites;
<note place="margin">Deut. 30.7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The Lord (ſaith hee) will curſe thy enemies, and them that hate thee, and perſecute thee; returne therefore, &amp; obey the voice of the Lord thy God, and do all his commandements. The ſame argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did <hi>Ioſhua</hi> vſe.
<note place="margin">Ioſ. 23.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The Lord ſaith he hath giuen you a land wherein you did not labor, citties which you builded not, and vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards which you planted not: now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore feare the Lord your God, &amp; ſerue him in vprightnes and truth. The ſame reaſon alſo doth the Lord (by <hi>Ieremy</hi>) vſe heere. Turne againe, and obey, and why? for I am your Lord. The ſame reaſon ought to moue euerie one of vs to feare the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.4.</note> for with him is mercie that hee may bee feared. Apply wee this to our ſelues. No nation hath bene longer vrged with this argument then our Engliſh nation: but hath it perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to obey the Lord? God indeed hath made vs his vineyard, and done for vs what he poſſibly could deuiſe, by pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting dreſſing hedging, watering, &amp; defending vs. Yet lo, nothing but ſower grapes. Nay haue we not degenerated more then any other nation? I would to god that we had not; for thus ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:184215:26"/>the caſe vvith vs: the more loue from God, the leſſe dutie from vs; the more mercy in God, the leſſe pittie in vs; the more peace, the leſſe quiet; the more knovvledge the leſſe practiſe: let enimies come, and we vvill hold together; let enemies go, and we fall out one vvith another; let ſickneſſe come, &amp; vve ſend for the preacher; let health come, and vve ſcorne the preacher; let death come, and ſome vvil giue a little to the poore; let life continue, &amp; they take al from the poore: when <hi>Dauid</hi> of loue ſent embaſſadors to viſit the king of Ammon,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o. 17.4.</note> they cut away halfe their beards, and curtoled their garments by the buttockes: but ſome ſeeke to cut their throats, which doe them moſt good, and that euen nowe. <hi>Ionathan</hi> vſed his fathers loue to <hi>Dauids</hi> benefit,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.36.</note> and by ſhooting of three arrowes, gaue him warning of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers diſpleaſure; but nowe many do abuſe their fathers loue, ſhooting poiſoned ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes at thoſe that are true of heart, cauſing diſpleaſure where none was, and that euen now: When God maketh men moſt able to do good, they are leaſt willing, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen now in the light of the goſpel. In time of dearth the rich hoord vp their corn, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtil for a greater price. In time of war and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon calamity, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men are infinitly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, then is euery man for himſelfe, ſetting
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:184215:26"/>the dice vppon men, taking fiue ſhillings for one, and 20. for fiue; but by the way, theſe be no vſurers, but deuills incarnate. One poore man beggeth of another. Eliah goeth to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repta, &amp; from thence to the rauens for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. <hi>Lazarus</hi> goeth to the rich mans gate, but the dogs giue him his alms. <hi>Nabals</hi> ſong is, I haue not for <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> when <hi>Nabal</hi> hath the deuill and all. Now do me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eate the calues of the ſtal, and the lambs of the flocke, drink wine out of golden cuppes, annoint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with coſtly ointment, wallow vpon beds of Iuorie, and ſing to the viall and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall inſtrument: and euen now, but <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> affliction is quite forgotten. When the Lorde ſpareth vs, wee ſmite our fellow ſeruaunts, when the Lorde forgiueth vs a thouſand talents, wee take our bretheren by the throate for euerie farthing. When God giueth <hi>Achab</hi> a kingdome, let <hi>Naboth</hi> looke to his vineyard. And when <hi>Achab</hi> is ſicke for <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, and <hi>Iezabell</hi> religious in proclaiming a faſte, for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabs</hi> ſickneſſe, then let <hi>Naboth</hi> looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his life. There is nothing but ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning houſe to houſe, and lande to lande, vntill there bee no more roome, except it bee for a plague. The Iſralites beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their earerings,
<note place="margin">Exod: 32.3.</note> and iewelles vppon a Calfe. The Papiſts like calues woulde
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:184215:27"/>beſtow all vpon the popes bull, and we like profane <hi>Eſau</hi> are content to ſel away our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly patrimonie for a meſſe of belly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and in this ſort we deale with the Lord, as though the Lord did ſpare vs, that wee might ſpare none; as though he did giue vs a portion to waſte prodigally; as though hee gaue vs our meate to play withall, and as though his mercie and goodneſſe, ſhoulde not make vs merciful and louing, and finally as though his long ſuffering and patience, were not to draw vs to repentance.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing that I obſerue from this place is this:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.4.</note> that ſeeing the loue of God is ſo free, ſo continuall, ſo vndeſerued, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable, that therefore we ought to ſet more by it, then by any loue in the world. Great was the loue of <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pithias,</hi> when one offered to die for the other, but it was neither free, perpetuall, nor vndeſerued; but god loued vs when we were his enimies, and hated him:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.10.</note> their loue ended with their liues, Gods loue is eternall, as himſelfe; the loue of Princes is great, but princes may be vnconſtant, as <hi>Saul</hi> was to <hi>Dauid.</hi> The loue of fathers is great, but they may proue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, as they which offered their ſonnes and daughters to the deuill. Many wiues be vnfaithfull as <hi>Dalila,</hi> ſcoffers as <hi>Michol.</hi> Children may proue vnnaturall as <hi>Abſalon</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:184215:27"/>was. Seruants are vntruſtie, as <hi>Gehezi.</hi> Friends are fained and ſickle as <hi>Ioab,</hi> and <hi>Iudas;</hi> but the louing kindneſſe of the Lord endureth for euer and euer, vppon ſuch as thinke vppon his commaundements to doe them.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.1</note> There are many things wanting in the world, which ſhould bring vs out of loue with the world. There wanteth abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the king of Samaria, willingnes in the wicked iudge, there wanteth iudgement in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſo as <hi>Iacob</hi> may deceiue him, fidelity is wanting in <hi>Laban,</hi> ſo that <hi>Iacob</hi> is deceiued, conſtancy is wanting in the Iewes, which wil crie, <hi>Crucifige,</hi> and <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> and almoſt all with a wind, ſo that Chriſt is executed: there wanted in <hi>Pharaoes</hi> butler thankfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his friend, ſo that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is forgotten: mercie in <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> wiſedome and diſcretion in his yong counſellers, and a good name in both is wanting, ſo that <hi>Quicquid del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rant reges plectuntur Achiui.</hi> The whole land ſmarted for their folly. In al men wanteth ſomewhat, the whole world hath not all things, no the worlde hath no intereſt in vs; for wee are choſen out of it, by that GOD that ſaith heere, <hi>I am your Lorde.</hi> There are not wanting the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, which like ſcorpions ſhould driue vs from the world to the Lord, as the malice of <hi>Cain,</hi> the hatred of <hi>Eſau,</hi> the villanie of <hi>Ioab,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:184215:28"/>the vnkindnes of <hi>Haman,</hi> the trechery of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> the cruelty of <hi>Iezabell,</hi> the ſicknes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab,</hi> the churliſhnes of <hi>Nabal,</hi> the diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of <hi>Ananias:</hi> as the breaſts of the world are not benointed onely with ſower things, but the verie milke that it yeeldeth bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it ſelfe, for all is but vanity, and vexation of ſpirite. There wanteth not ignorance, weakenes, vnwillingnes, vnfaithfulnes in all, imperfections in the beſt, nothing certaine, but al changable as the moone, fading as the flours of the field, &amp; vaniſhing as the ſmoke in the aire, al waxe old as a garment, and as a veſture ſhall we all be changed. What ſhal I ſay? the whole world is ſet on miſchiefe. But with the Lord our god the caſe is otherwiſe, for he is almighty, &amp; therfore of ability to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the godly, &amp; to puniſh the wicked. He is our father in Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; therfore wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receiue vs when we turne vnto him, he is alſo a iuſt God, &amp; therefore wil plague thoſe which wil not turne vnto him, he hath al knowledge, &amp; knoweth al things, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will knowe <hi>Barrabas</hi> from <hi>Barnabas, Eſau</hi> from <hi>Iacob, Bethauen</hi> from <hi>Bethel. Simon Magus</hi> from <hi>Simon Peter. Iudas Iſcariot</hi> from <hi>Iudas</hi> the brother of <hi>Iames, Shibboleth</hi> from <hi>Sibboleth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10.</note> and who ſhall deceiue the Lord? He is not as the ſonne of man that he ſhould change his mind, &amp; therefore he muſt needs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:184215:28"/>be conſtant, and his counſell ſhall ſtand.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 135.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> He cannot be letted or his purpoſe, for he is in heauen, &amp; doth whatſoeuer he wil:
<note place="margin">Eſa. 49.</note> he cannot forget his children, for he hath written them in the palms of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 121.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> He is always watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ouer his children, for he that keepeth Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell doth neither ſlumber nor ſleepe. A ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond information ſhal not miſcarrie him, for hee that knoweth all at once needeth no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. No oratour ſhal turne his mind, for he wil neuer alter the decree that is gone out of his mouth, yea his counſel muſt needs ſtand, againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no wiſedom, no counſel, nor ſtrength can preuaile.
<note place="margin">Pro. 21.30.</note> If he hath concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued any diſpleaſure againſt his children hee wil ſoon be intreated vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance:
<note place="margin">Pſa. 103.</note> he calleth vs, he perſwadeth vs, he entreateth vs to turne &amp; obey him, &amp; therfore let vs turne againe: he claimeth it as his right, it is for our benifit, he ſhal get nothing by our ſeruice: if vve neuer ſerue him, he vvil looſe nothing by vs, if we be ſaued, he ſhalbe glorified, &amp; if we be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, he vvilbe glorified alſo: for no vvay vvil he looſe a iot of his glory, &amp; therfore let vs turne again &amp; obey him, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth it in his law, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, Thou ſhalt haue no other gods but me; we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fes it in our beliefe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vve ſay, I beleeue in God the father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty: we pray for it whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay; our father hallowed be thy name, &amp;c. &amp; therfore if we
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:184215:29"/>doe not turne againe, we breake his law, we deny our faith, and we mocke God himſelfe in our prayers. His mercies ſhould moue vs to obedience, his promiſes ſhuld allure vs to obey him. If he correct vs, it is that we might obey him; if he plague vs, it is becauſe we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him not; but if he doth beare with vs, and forbeare vs, it is, to ſee whether his long ſuffering and patience will drawe vs to repentance. The Lord is our Lord, and ſtil offreth vs mercie, we are his children and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes owe him duetie: hee is our Lorde in goodnes, power, wiſedome, iuſtice, mercie, prouidence, and in himſelfe aboue all, and therefore let vs turne vnto him. God for his mercies ſake turne our hearts that he may be ſtill our God, and wee may be his people for euer, So be it. <hi>Now let vs pray.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <head>The ſecond Sermon of God wooing his Church.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREMIE Chap. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 14</hi>
                     </bibl> O ye diſobedient children, turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſaith the Lord, for I am your Lord, and I will take you one of a citie, and two of a tribe, and will bring you to Zion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 15</hi>
                     </bibl> And I will giue you Paſtors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mine heart, which ſhall feede you with knowledge and vnderſtanding.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:184215:29"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the former part of this text, the Lord hath ſhewed what authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and power hee hath ouer his people, by which he might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them to ſerue him: but now he taketh another courſe, whereas hee might enforce them, he doth intreate them; and whereas hee might preſſe them downe with moſt greeuous iudgements, he doth now promiſe to reward them moſt liberally, and to deale moſt bountifully with them, for he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to endow them with the beſt, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt bleſsings which hee giueth vnto any of the ſons of men in this life. For firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they were in captiuitie and bondage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Gods enemies, hee promiſeth to ſet them at libertie, in their owne countrie, and to eſtabliſh his true religion and worſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. And further, that they may no more prouoke the wrath of the Lorde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them through their ignoraunce, and wandring out of the way for want of lightes and guides; hee promiſeth to prouide for them ſuch paſtours as ſhall watch ouer them for their good, and not ſee them want anie inſtruction; as if he ſhould ſay vnto them, I will bring you to my own houſe, and during your whole life I will aſſure you of the beſt things I haue for you, and you ſhal want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if you will obey me, this ſhal be your
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:184215:30"/>dowrie. And thus we ſee how frankely the Lord dealeth with them, and what large of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers he maketh them, as one which mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to winne them, if any thing will wooe them.</p>
            <p>And further, leſt that ſuch as were well affected, and deſirous to returne indeede, might be diſcouraged, thinking it in vaine to turne, except al would turne; and becauſe the promiſe was made to al the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, it would not auaile them to humble themſelues. The Lorde (to take away that doubt) telleth them, that though but a few of them do returne, yet hee will be as good as his word: and if but one of a city, and two of a tribe, that is, very few in compariſon of the whole; yet if ſo many ſhall in trueth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, they ſhall not looſe their labour, but the Lord will bleſſe them, and the reſt for their ſakes. Thus the Lord ſheweth himſelf carefull to remooue all cauſes of doubting from his people, and to put in all the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoes that may be on their behalfe, al to make the conueiaunce of his bleſsinges as ſure as may be vnto them, that they may haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to allege for themſelues, if they ſhuld vnkindly reiect or neglect this gracious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of the Lord, ſo mercifully and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruedly offered vnto them.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that from hence wee may
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:184215:30"/>learne, is this, that the ſinnes of many ſhall not hinder the courſe of Gods mercies vnto the penitent, though they be but few. The Sodomites were many, and their ſinnes were as a mightie pile of woode for the wrath of the Lord to burne vpon, the crie of them aſcended vp vnto the eares of the Lord, and the filthineſſe of their abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions had infected the very aire; yet all this could not moue the Lord to keep backe his mercy and louing kindeneſſe from righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Lot,</hi> whoſe ſoule was vexed within him for their wickednes;
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.29.</note> neither did the Lorde forget his ſeruant <hi>Abraham</hi> when the fire of his fierce wrath was flaming vpon thoſe wicked cities. In the like gracious manner did hee remember <hi>Rahab</hi> (who gaue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement to the ſpies of <hi>Ioſhua</hi>) when Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho was vtterly deſtroyed. And this is a point of ſingular comfort to the godly, to remember, that God in viſiting the ſinnes of the whole world, yet will not forget to ſhew mercie vnto thouſands of them that loue him and keepe his commaundements. Yea, if there bee but one of a Citie, and twoo of a Tribe that doe truely returne to the Lord, the Lord wil ſurely embrace them whatſoeuer others do.</p>
            <p>Againe, we are further to obſerue heere, that the Lorde that is the moſt righteous
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:184215:31"/>Iudge of the world, iudging all men in equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and trueth, will not condemne all for the wickedneſſe of ſome, but will take them as he findeth them, if there be but one of a cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or two of a tribe that feare God, they ſhall be iuſtified in their vprightneſſe, and not be condemned with the reſt And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is a good rule for vs to follow, that in cenſuring and iudging of men we may take heede of raſh and haſtie iudgement, for it is the maner of the peruerſe world to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn all for ſome, without any difference, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. If in the miniſtery they heare of ſom one or a few that be of lewd and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behauiour, ſtraitwayes their bolt is ſhot ouer the heads of all that are in the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, crying out that all be naught, they are al ſuch. In like ſort, if any other man that is a profeſſor of the goſpel chance to be founde in any fault, ſtraitwayes profane Atheiſts crie out with open mouth, that there are none worſe then profeſſours: but they will take heede (I hope) how they do make ſuch wry mouthed concluſions againſt al eſtates, for feare that their necke ſhoulde pay the price of their tongue. For if they ſhould look into the ſtate of Kings and Princes, they ſhould finde that ſome haue beene vſurpers, ſome idolaters, ſome tyrants, and ſome verie vicious and licentious perſons; will they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:184215:31"/>therefore conclude and ſay of Kinges and Princes, as they doe of the poore miniſters and other inferior profeſſors of the Goſpel, there are none worſe then Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for ſuch and ſuch were idolaters, &amp;c. they are all naught? No, I trow not, for feare of a worſe matter. But doe they thinke in this ſort to depraue and condemne the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of the goſpel, and the knowledge of the ſacred ſcriptures as the cauſe of al diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the profeſſours of the ſame as the worſt perſons that liue (as the maner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is) and to eſcape the Lords hands for this their horible pride, and preſumptuous raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: wil not the Lord (thinke we) be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of ſuch wicked ones that ſhall ſo malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly beare falſe witnes againſt Gods church and ſlander the Lord Ieſus in his poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers? Is not the Lord as ielous of his owne glorie, and of the credit of his people and goſpel, as Kings and princes are of theirs, and their lawes? but as Chriſt ſaid of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſo wee may truely ſay of ſuch ſwift iudges, they knowe not what ſpirite they are of. For the ſpirit of God taketh an other courſe, hauing to deale with the ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Aſia, in the Reuelation he ſaith thus:
<note place="margin">Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> I know thy faith, and thy patience, and thy loue, and thy zeale, &amp;c. that is, I commend thee for theſe good things, and I approue
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:184215:32"/>thy workes, but yet I haue ſomwhat to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee for ſuch a thing and ſuch a thing; that is, I neither condemne thy good, bicauſe of thy euill, nor commend the euill that is in thee, becauſe of thy good things: this courſe he taketh with euerie one of them, to ſhew what we ſhould do in ſuch caſes, if we haue the ſpirit of god; for we ſo many in the world fallen into two foule extremities at this day: firſt our proteſtants at large ſay, that becauſe wee haue the goſpell plentifully taught in many places of the land, and the ſacraments, &amp; many good things (the Lord make vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede thankfull for them) that therefore all is well, and nothing is amiſſe, there are no faults, nor corruptions in the church, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or people. The Browniſts on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide crie out, that becauſe that there are ſome defects and wantes in the church, and euerie thing is not ineuerie reſpect ſo pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reformed as it ought to be by the word, therefore (ſay they) wee haue no church, no ſacraments, no miniſters, nor any thing that is good, but that al our miniſters are dum dogges, <hi>Baals</hi> prieſts, and I know not what, playing the franticke mans part, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome thing lieth in his way, or there is ſomething in the houſe that is not to his minde, therefore laieth about him at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that commeth in his way; the poore
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:184215:32"/>innocent children are beaten, the ſeruaunts driuen out of doores, the meate on the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is caſt downe to the dogges, the fire flung about the houſe, the windowes are broken in peeces: and not content with this, runneth out and gathereth vppe al the filth and dirt in the ſtreete to caſt in his mothers face that bare him, and wipeth his handes vppon his fathers face who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate him, and all to make them odious to all that ſhall beholde them. And hauing ſet the houſe on a fire, runneth away by the light thereof, crying out to all that they haue infected with the like rage. Come out from among them, Come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, there is no dwelling, there is no houſe, there is no meate, there is no body to dreſſe anie thing, they are al polluted and defiled, all is naught amongſt them. And hauing made their Proclamation, away they fling into another countrey, till they haue done as great an exploite there, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till at the laſt falling out amongeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and excommunicating one another, many of them return home againe &amp; as men awaked out of their dreame, they lay downe their weapon, and goe quietly to bedde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. And in the like ſort doe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts deale with vs; but their dealing is ſo groſſe &amp; palpable, that I wil not vouchſafe to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:184215:33"/>vvaſte any breath about them. But novv to the text againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One of a citie and two of a tribe, &amp;c.]</hi> Here vve are further to obſerue, that God is not led by the multitude of the vvicked, to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of the godly being but fevv, or to like vvell of the euill, becauſe they are many, vvhich is alſo a rule for vs to immitate and follovv, and it may ſtand vs in ſteed many vvaies,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 23.2.</note> for firſt it teacheth vs to take heede that vve be not dravven avvay to euill, vvith the example of the multitude vvhich like a mighty ſtreame is very forcible to carry vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay, except vve row hard againſt the ſame. The life of the multitude is called by our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt the broad vvay,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 7.13.</note> that is, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvay, vvherein many doe vvalke vnto their deſtruction, vvhich therefore muſt bee auoided of euerie one that vvill be ſaued: ſecondly vve may learne from hence, not to be diſcouraged from good things, by reaſon of the ſmall number that ioyne vvith vs, for ſtraight is the gate and narrovv is the vvay that leadeth to ſaluation, and fevv there bee that find it. And thirdly vve may ſee here, that multitude is no certaine argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the truth, nor of the beſt things, as Papiſts and Atheiſts doe imagin, for though euill men haue all the hands and feales in the vvorld to teſtifie in their behalfe, yet are they neuer
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:184215:33"/>the better before God, as <hi>Achabs</hi> iourney was neuer the more proſperous (when hee went contrarie to Gods will againſt <hi>Ramoth Gilead</hi>) though foure hundred falſe prophets ſaid vnto him, <hi>go and proſper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and but one onely was againſt him in it. And though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny laugh thee to ſcorne, thou art neuer the worſe, if thou haſt the truth on thy ſide: as <hi>Micaiah</hi> was neuer the worſe though 400. were againſt him, and the king and all were againſt him, yet was the truth ſtil the truth, (though it were iuſtified only in his mouth) and preuailed at the laſt. We ſee for the moſt parte, that thoſe which turne to God as <hi>Hezechias</hi> did, are but the ſmalleſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as it were one or twoo in a towne (in compariſon) that are truely religious, and a few in a great congregation, that are zelous indeede for the glorie of God, and they are alſo noted &amp; pointed at of the reſt, as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wonderments of the world: and yet we muſt beware, that we make not vp the whole reckoning, with thoſe only which we ſee, or can yet iudge of (as the Browniſts do) exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the reſt, but to thinke thus rather, that as there may bee fire vnder the aſhes, though I ſee it not, yet ſo there may be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the harts of many though I ſee it not yet. And as in the daies of <hi>Eliah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19.18.</note> the lord had 7000. in Iſraell which neuer bowed their
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:184215:34"/>knees to <hi>Baal</hi> which <hi>Eliah</hi> could not ſee, as ſharpe ſighted as he was, ſo there may bee in our daies ſeauen thouſand, which belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God and may proue religious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> we ſee now, and yet we be not ſo ſharp ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as <hi>Eliah</hi> was. But howſoeuer it may be, this is ſure, that the ſincere worſhippers of God are alwaies the feweſt; and Gods num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is alwaies the ſmalleſt. And therefore as <hi>Ieremy</hi> preached to all, but conuerted by his doctrine not paſt one of a Cittie, and two of a tribe, that is, a verie fewe. So we now muſt preach to all, but if one of a citie, and two of a tribe, that is, if anie at all doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit at our preaching, wee may thinke our ſelues verie happie. It may be, that as 70. followed Chriſt a while, which bare the name of Chriſts diſcrples, beſides thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that followed him for their bellies ſake, ſo many may follow vs nowe in the like manner: but as theſe ſeuentie diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples came after twelue, ſo is it nowe, that as it is read in one place, of Chriſt and his ſeuentie, and in another place, of Chriſt and his twelue, ſo nowe may wee ſee the like againe: for at one time you ſhall ſee Chriſt with a great auditorie, and ſome time Chriſt with twoo or three about him, from ſeuentie to twelue; and amongſt thoſe fewe will bee ſome hypocrites and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:184215:34"/>falſe brethren too, as amongeſt the twelue there was found one <hi>Iudas</hi> a traitour. So that the Lords companie oftentimes prooueth like <hi>Gideons</hi> armie againſt the <hi>Midianites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 7.4,</note> which at the firſt was 32000. amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt which were found 22000. timerous and fearefull, which being diſmiſſed, there remained but 10000. of which ten thouſand there were founde but 300. which would take paines to lap water like a dogge, and they were <hi>Gede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> army, ſo from two and thirtie thouſand they came downe to 300. The ſame is ſtil to be obſerued, which hath beene from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and ſhall continue to the end.
<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.66.</note> In going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god many are noted in the goſpel. 70. diſciples forſake Chriſt at one time for one ſpeech which they vnderſtood not, and came no more at him afterward, yea &amp; it was doubtfull whether the reſt would haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken him too: but in comming vnto Chriſt but few are noted, nowe and then one alone like <hi>Nicodemus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.2.</note> and that by might too for feare of the Iewes. Inquirie being made for prophets, four hundred falſe, but one tru, four hundred againſt God, but one for God can be founde. In the ninth of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> wee reade of ſixe that were ſent to deſtroie, and but one to ſaue. In the fifth of <hi>Ieremie</hi> the Prophet is willed to ſearche all Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem; to ſee if hee coulde finde but one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:184215:35"/>righteous man that the Lorde might ſpare the city for his ſake. Now, this is hard, and it goeth ſo hard,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.32.</note> that when all are gleaned out and refined, the Lordes flocke will bee but a little flocke as Chriſt calleth it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the multitude, but it is the beſt flocke.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Gideons</hi> army was but the gleaning of Ephraim, yet thoſe gleanings were better then the vintage of <hi>Abiezer;</hi> ſo the Lordes people are but the gleanings of the worlde, yet thoſe gleanings are better then the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of Sathan. And as hard as it goeth, ſo mercifull is the Lord, that if in all Sodome there be found but one <hi>Lot,</hi> the Lorde will gleane him out, before the deuill ſhall reape his harueſt. If one groat be loſt, he will ſeek it vp againe; if one ſheepe be gone aſtray, he will fetch him home againe with ioy; if one ſinner repenteth,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 15.7</note> there ſhall be ioy for him amongſt the angels in heauen; if one prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall child commeth home againe, hee ſhall be receiued; if one leaper amongſt ten that are clenſed, returne with his thanks, he ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be accepted; if in a cittie one, in a tribe but two, and in a whole world but eight iuſt perſons bee founde, the Lord will receiue them and ſaue them from periſhing with the wicked world. The Lorde dealeth not with his people as men doe, that will ſay, if there be but one fiſh in the net, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:184215:35"/>one, caſt it in againe; if there come vppe but a little fruit vpon the tree, let the ſwine eate it, except there were more; if the henne bringeth but one chickin, caſt it away, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are no more; or as the wicked ſay, if there bee but one or two in a congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation that feare God, what account make you of him, hee is one, we are many againſt one? but the Lord makes much of one, ſo it bee his owne, to teach vs, that we alſo ſhould make more account of one good man, (if there be but one among many) then of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bad, as the Lord doth, for he dealeth like a merciful creditor, who hauing many deſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate debts, will take any thing, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe part, becauſe he cannot haue all. Laſt of all, from this place we note, that the Lord vſeth to ſpare many wicked ones oftentimes for the ſmal number of his elect ſake which are amongſt them, as he ſpared Sodom and Gomorrha for <hi>Lots</hi> ſake, the olde world for <hi>Noahs</hi> ſake, and <hi>Putiphar</hi> for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſake, the thornes are ſpared for the Lillies ſake that groweth amongſt them, and the tares for the wheate ſake, are not cutte downe, and for good <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> his ſake it was that the Lordes Prophet vouchſafed to goe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wicked <hi>Iehoram,</hi> or elſe hee would not ſo much as haue looked towardes that wicked man, though he were a king.
<note place="margin">2 King. 3.1</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:184215:36"/>
            <p> This may teach vs to make much of them that feare God, for if their number be once acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed, the world is at an end; for as the world was made at the firſt for their ſakes, ſo for their ſakes it is that it continueth and ſtandeth: for how long did Sodom ſtand free from the fire of Gods wrath after <hi>Lot</hi> and his houſholde were remooued out of it? or how long did the old world eſcape drowning af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that <hi>Noah</hi> and his companie were entred the Arke, no longer ſhall the world ſtand, after that the Lord hath once gathered his choſen vnto himſelfe. If the wicked did wel conſider of this point, that when the Lord hath gathered his wheate into his barne (as the Lord Ieſus ſaith) that hee will then ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the tares together and caſt them into vnquenchable fire, they woulde not bee ſo haſtie to driue away Gods people, and to hunt them out of their companie, and out of their Citties and townes, as they doe, like the Galileans which were not well vntill Chriſt were gone out of their coaſt, but euen in pollicie they make much of him, as fome doe of wardes, whoſe landes they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy but during their minoritie and the terme of their liues, and after their deceaſe, or when they come to full age, all goeth from them againe to another. But nowe let vs come to the text againe.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:184215:36"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>And wil bring you to Zion]</hi> Zion was a fort in Ieruſalem,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 5.7. 2. Sam. 6.16 1. King. 8.1</note> &amp; kept in poſſeſsion of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſites til <hi>Dauids</hi> time, but it was won by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> when he came to the crowne. After hee had won it, hee brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hither the Arke of Gods couenant; to which place the people reſorted to worſhip the Lord. So that by Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is meant the place of Gods worſhip and religion, ſo that the meaning of the Lorde in theſe words is this in reſpect, I wil ſet you at libertie from your enemies, and bring you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to your owne country, that you may ſerue mee in holy exerciſes of religion, as I haue appointed. Whence we may note, that the end of the churches deliuerance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any trouble and affliction, is to become more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, for to this end hath the Lord deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs out of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our enemies, that we might ſerue him without feare,
<note place="margin">Luke. 1.74.</note> in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; true holines alwaies. But ſom may ſay: This is a mater of no great vaiue, for they had it before &amp; made no reckoning of it, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very like that this wold not moue them. But if hee had tolde them of their gorgeous houſes, delicate orchards, pleaſant fields, and abundance of worldly wealth and great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and dignities, it may bee they woulde haue regarded ſuch things, as ſathan thought to mooue Chriſt to worſhippe him that waie, when no waie elſe woulde preuaile,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:184215:37"/>he ſheweth him therefore all the kingdomes of the world, and the glorie of them, and doth offer them al vnto him vpon condition that he would fall downe and worſhip him, but by no means he could preuaile with his goodly offer, for the Lord Ieſus was not of a worldlings mind, that will do more for gold then for godlineſſe. So it ſhould ſeeme that if the Lord had told the Iewes of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, wherewith the heart of man is more drawen, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſpiritual matters, he might haue wonne their loue for euer. But to tell them of Zion, and religion, of paſtours, and preaching, might ſeeme to be the next way to driue them further from his loue then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Indeede this ſeemeth to bee a good worldly pollicie, but the Lord neede not to be taught of the world. The truth is ſo, that when they had their fill of religion and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious exerciſes at Zion, they cared not for them: but now being wel humbled with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction amongſt idolaters and ſcoffers: and being kept from it, they account deerely of it. And the trueth of this may further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that pittifull complaint and mone which they make in the 137.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 137 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> pſalme, when they were amongſt the Babylonians in cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, <hi>By the riuers of Babel we ſate, and there we wept, when we remembred Zion:</hi> they wept not before, when they were at Zion, but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:184215:37"/>now they weep: yea ſo great was their griefe at the remembrance of Zion nowe, that all mirth and muſicke is laide aſide: nowe they hung vp their harpes vpon the willow trees, and fall to weeping and ſorrowing for Zion; for Zion, why could not their melodie and ſweete muſicke make them merry? Oh no, no, they could take no ioy nor comfort in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch outward things, ſo long as they were baniſhed from the publique exerciſes of Gods religion at Zion, which was a ſigne of Gods loue and fauour vnto them; but nowe they were excommunicate and caſt out as it were vnſauourie ſalt vpon the dunghill (for Babylon was but a dunghill to Zion) oh God had taken his loue tokens and iewelles from them, God ſhewed an angry countenaunce vpon them. How could they then be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? what ioy could they haue in the riuers, or pleaſant walkes, or ſweete muſicke when they remembred Zion? oh now Zion, Zion,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 137,</note> Zion, nothing but Zion would make them weepe, and daſhed all their ioy and mirth, &amp; laied it in the duſt, But, was this all? Oh no, no, beſides all this, they that led vs captiues required of vs ſongs, and mirth, when wee had hanged vppe our harpes, ſaying, ſing vs one of the ſongs of Zion. Oh the wicked Babylonians came ſcoffingly, and taunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and mocked them by their religion, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:184215:38"/>flowted at the very name of God which was praiſed in their ſongs, and this cut the very heart ſtrings of them in twain: as the proud Spaniard would ſcoffe at vs and our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Lord (as iuſtly he might) ſhould deliuer vs into their handes; Come on you Proteſtants would they ſay, let vs heare now one of your Geneua pſalmes, &amp;c. Oh this would go to the heart of vs (if wee had anie ſparke of Gods ſpirite in vs) to heare God thus, and his holy religion had in deriſion of his wicked enemies.</p>
            <p>Here then we may learne, that wee neuer ſee what a benefit it is to haue religion, and the miniſtery of the word, vntill it be taken from vs.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.3.</note> Though <hi>Dauid</hi> alwayes loued reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, yet neuer ſo much as when hee was in trouble and baniſhment, for then he coulde make his mone vnto God, and ſay, that the ſparrowes and the ſwallowes were at a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſe then he, becauſe they might come and build their neſts neere vnto the altar of the Lord, and they could haue a place in the Lords houſe when hee was ſhut out. Then did his ſoule long for the preſence of the Lord againe.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 42.1.</note> As the Hart longeth for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when ſhee is chaſed; then was his meate nothing but teares, and his drincke ſtil min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with weeping, and then did he poure out his ſoule vnto God like water, and his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:184215:38"/>bones were as it were cut a ſunder, ſo great was his griefe then, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he remembred how he had gone with the multitude into the houſe of the Lorde with ſongs of praiſe, and thankſgiuing as vnto a feaſt which nowe he could not do.
<note place="margin">Amos. 8.14.</note> And this is that which <hi>Amos</hi> prophecieth of, when the Lord ſhall bring a famine of the word of god vpon the land, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall men run vp and downe from one place vnto another, yea from one ſea to another; and from North to South to ſeeke it, and ſhal not finde it, for he that wanteth meate, and health, and libertie, can beſt tell what they be worth.</p>
            <p>And the rather to prouoke vs to a loue of theſe heauenly things, we are to note, that religion and libertie goe both together: The Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> neuer proſpered better then when they embraced moſt zealouſly the worde of the Lorde. And moſt true is that ſaying of the Lorde Ieſus, that if wee firſt ſeeke (as many did) the king dome of GOD, and the righteouſneſſe thereof,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> then libertie, then peace, then health, then riches, and then all other things ſhalbe caſt vpon vs. It foloweth.</p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>And I will giue you Paſtours according to my heart.]</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, whereas before you went into captiuitie, you had pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours that were either dumbe dogges that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:184215:39"/>could not teach you at all, or falſe prophets that taught as it ſtoode with their aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſo that you could neither haue knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor conſcience to ſerue me; for which cauſe I ſent you into captiuitie,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.13.</note> nowe I will not only bring you home againe, but I will alſo giue you wiſe and godly paſtours which may teach you how to ſerue me rightly, and may alſo call vpon you to ſerue me faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that you may goe no more into captiuity. Here then we may note firſt, that a wiſe and a learned miniſterie is a moſt needful thing, in aſmuch as without it, it is not poſsible tru religion ſhoulde continue. And therefore when God beganne an ordinary religion, he commanded that <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes, and the tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> ſhould be ſanctified to the office of prieſthoode, to offer ſacrifices for the ſinnes of the people, and to teach and inſtruct them in the vvill of the Lord, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby that religion could not be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden without ſome ſpecial means to teach and direct the people therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to my heart;</hi> that is, ſuch as I ſhall like and approue, that ſhall haue their calling from me, and their gifts from mee, and their allovvance from me, and ſhal teach for me, and reproue for me, and ſhall ſeeke nothing but my glorie, and your good, ſuch as my ſelfe ſhall like of; ſo is <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaide to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:184215:39"/>be a man after Gods ovvne heart, that is, ſuch a one as God taketh delight in, and approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and that is Gods heart indeed: for the Lord hath no heart, nor head, nor body, nor hands, nor feete, nor eies, nor mouth, nor eares as man hath, and as the groſe Papiſtes haue ſet him out in their pictures vpon their vvindovves, &amp;c. But theſe partes of man are attributed and giuen to God after the manner of men, for mans better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the nature of God; for euery man knovveth to vvhat vſe theſe partes of mans body ſerue; the eie to ſee by, the eare to heare by, the mouth to ſpeake by, the hand to worke by, the foote to goe by. And ſometime theſe partes in man are in the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures put for the qualities and properties that be in them; and ſometime for the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and deedes that are vvrought by them, as appeareth in the fift chapter of the goſpel after Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> vvhere it is ſaid by our ſauiour Chriſt; if thy eie offend thee, plucke it out, or if thy hand offend thee, cut it off: his meaning is, that men ſhould take heede of ſuch things as are done by the hand, and by the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; and ſo by the reſt, to the offence of God or our neighbour. And it is an vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thing in our common ſpeaking amongſt men, vvhen vve ſee any mans vvriting, we ſay, this is ſuch a mannes hand, and yet the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:184215:40"/>writing is not his hand, but his handy worke. When we heare one ſpeake, wee vſe to ſay; that is ſuch a mans tongue, or, I knovve him by his tongue, and yet his ſpeech is not his tongue, but a thing vttered by the meanes of his tongue. So likewiſe in God there are ſuch properties and qualities, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his very eſſence and being, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Scriptures, for our better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding what the Lorde is vnto vs; as knovvledge, and wiſedome, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and might, and ſtrength, and iuſtice, and mercy, and prouidence, and loue, and hatred, and anger, and liking, and diſliking, and many moe, vvhich are all ſet foorth, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder the partes of mans body, or by other creatures whoſe natures are very well knowen vnto men. And how could we bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter come vnto the knowledge of Gods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable nature, ſo farre as is meete for vs to knovve, but by ſuch things as we are familiarly acquainted vvithall our ſelues? for doe not al men know, that ſtrength doth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her force by the meanes of the arme? and that knovvledge and vnderſtanding doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the heart by the eie and the eare? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o not men declare their mind by word and by writing? doeth not loue and anger lodge in the heart? and doth not the countenaunce bevv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay the liking and diſliking that is in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:184215:40"/>the heart? and who is ſo ſimple that knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not theſe things? Therefore when the ſimpleſt ſhall heare the ſcriptures call God a ſpirite, and tell vs withall, that a ſpirit hath no fleſh nor bones as men haue, and yet ſhal heare the ſame Scriptures to attribute vnto God a head, a heart, together with eies, and eares, and a mouth, and a face, and a ſoule, and feete, and ſuch like, as if he were not a ſpirit, but a man, muſt they not needes conceiue that there is ſomething elſe meant by ſuch kinde of ſpeeches, which they could not ſo vvell vnderſtand, nay not at all conceiue, if God ſhould vtter himſelfe as hee is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and not by ſuch things as are familiar with mans vnderſtanding, and not to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine ſo groſly as the groſe headed idolatrous Papiſts do, that God is a man indeede, and hath the parts of mans body indeede? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvhen vve heare of the Lords hand or arme, vvhat can we vnderſtand thereby but his omnipotent power, might, and ſtrength, vvhereby he is able to do all things which he vvill doe? Other arme and other hand the Lorde hath not, for he is a ſpirit. When we heare of the Lords eies and eares, vvhat can we conceiue thereby, but his knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding, which is ſuch that nothing can be hidden from his maieſtie? but that he ſeeth and knoweth all things at one inſtant?
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:184215:41"/>other eares and other eies, the Lord hath not, for hee is a ſpirit. When we heare of the mouth of the Lord, what elſe can we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thereby but the reuelation of his will? other mouth the Lord hath not, for hee is a ſpirit. When we heare the Lords head is as white as wooll, what can we gather thereby but the eternal wiſdom of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.14.</note> becauſe wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly attributed to the grey hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? other head and haire the Lord hath not, for he is a ſpirit. When we hear of the ſoul or heart of God, what can we concerue thereby but the Lords liking or diſliking of a thing? otherwiſe the Lord hath neither heart nor ſoule, for hee is a ſpirit. When we heare of the light of Gods countenance,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 46.</note> what elſe can we vnderſtand thereby but the tokens of his loue and fauor? otherwiſe the Lord hath no countenance, ſmiling, or frowning as men haue, for he is a ſpirit. And when we heare that God is a ſpirit, wee muſt not concerue thereby, that God is circumſcribed within any certaine place, as ſome heretikes haue thought,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtici.</note> becauſe a ſpirit is ſo; but we are to learne thereby, that he is of a ſpirituall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and inuiſible nature, but altogether vnſpeakeable, infinite, and incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And thus we ſee what is meant by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours according to Gods heart, that is, ſuch as his maieſtie ſhall approoue and like of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:184215:41"/>Nowe let vs ſee what wee may learne from hence. The Lord promiſing and purpoſing to do his people good, yea the greateſt good that can be if they turne to him, he ſaith, he wil gaue them paſtors according to his lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſuch as he ſhall approue and delight in; to teach vs that there can come no good vnto Gods people but by ſuch meanes as God doth like of. To build vp Gods church in faith and repentance, and to keepe the ſame in the holy obedience of Gods lawes; there is more required then to haue paſtors, and dctours, they muſt be ſuch as God doth like of. Theſe are tokens of Gods loue to his people, and ſhal do good in their places, and turne many vnto righteouſneſſe, where others are tokens of Gods wrath, and are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in his wrath, as <hi>Saul</hi> was to the Iſraelites, to be a plague vnto the people. Theſe that are approued of God, haue their gifts from God, and are ſent forth with his bleſsing, that they may proſper &amp; beget many ſoules to God. The other are made barren, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed that they can doe nothing, but onely ſupply the place of paſtours, but the ſheepe cannot feede in their paſtures it is ſo ſower; or if they feede, they cannot thriue, becauſe it is not bleſſed, for as the body liueth not by bread onely, ſo the ſoule liueth not by doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine onely, but by the bleſsing of God vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:184215:42"/>both. <hi>Daniels</hi> diet was but water &amp; pulſe, yet with that did hee like better, then they which had their porcion from the kings ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe it was Gods allowance, and went with a bleſsing. So they that haue paſtours according to the Lords own heart, are many times fed but with plaine, yet pure doctrine, and their ſoules are better fed with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; their faith is more ſtrong, their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is more ſincere, and their life more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, then theirs that are fed after a more ſtately and princely manner, which oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of humane learning and eloquence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it it is gods allowance and goeth with a bleſſing, whereas the other commeth and goeth like the winde, which onely puffeth and bloweth at men, and ſo leaueth them as it found them. In the twenty three of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> the Lorde doth moſt notably deſcribe ſuch prophets, as are not according to his heart. In the 23 hee calleth them liars and dreamers, to ſhewe that there is no credit to be giuen vnto them, more then vnto hars, neither is there in their doctrine any more certainetie then is in a dreame. In the ſixe and twentieth verſe hee ſaith, they delight in lies, which he calleth the deceit of their owne heartes, to ſhewe from what foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine they draw all their licor, euen out of the filthy puddles of their owne braine. In
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:184215:42"/>the twenty ſeuen verſe hee ſheweth what is the fruit of theſe dreames, namely the name of God is forgottten by their meanes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the people, a moſt horrible ſinne to forget GOD, as if the deuill himſelfe ſhould teach. In the thirtie verſe he calleth them theeues, becauſe they ſteale the word of GOD away from the people, like thoſe that are ſtill diſſembling and diſcouraging men from the reading of the ſcripitures af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of the popiſh ſynagogue, for feare that their wickedneſſe ſhoulde be deſcried by the light of the worde. They that robbe by the high waie, take awaie but mens money or their worldly goodes, but theſe robbe mens ſoules of the moſt precious worde of GOD, therefore they are the greateſt theeues. And the better to effect their purpoſe the Lorde ſayth in the one and thirtieth verſe that they haue verie ſweete tongues, and can make the people beleeue that the Lord ſaith this, and the Lord ſaith that, when it is onely the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of their owne heart. In the two and thirtieth verſe he ſaith, they are flatterers, and through their flatterie they cauſe the people to erre; &amp; in a word he ſaith, that the Lord neuer ſent them, neither gaue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny authority, and therefore they bring no profite vnto the people, they preach and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:184215:43"/>ſtudie and take paines to no purpoſe, like the good wife that churmeth, and churmeth and can make no butter come. As for the people that l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue vnder their miniſterie, hee ſheweth in the 2. verſe that they be adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and ſwearers, full of wickednes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlines, to ſhew that nothing but wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can grow vppon the ground that is til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſuch as are not according to the Lords liking. As for their owne behauiour hee ſheweth in the thirteenth and fourteenth verſes that it is ſutable to their teaching: deceitfull and filthie; broken out with all manner of botches and blaines, of fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and filthynes, and adulterie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanenes, and walking in the by-pathes of lies and falſhood, ſtrengthning the hands of the wicked, that none can returne for his wickedneſſe, and in one word more, they are all, both prophets and people vnto mee, but as Sodom a ſinke of ſinne, and as the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Gomorrha ſuch an other ſinke: this they are to me ſaith the Lord, thus they are in my eie whatſoeuer they ſeeme to be in their owne opinion, or in the iudgement of others whome they haue blinded and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched: Thus we ſee what vgly creatures they are which runne before the Lord ſend them, which are miniſters after mens hearts, but not after Gods heart, as a number of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:184215:43"/>blind guides amongſt vs bee; the Lorde ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no pleaſure in them, nor in thoſe foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh people that are contented with them: and therefore ſets them alone to do as they liſt, and turneth them as falſe children, ouer whom he hath no care, but lets them runne as it were filth and vermine for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming &amp; waſhing with the water of his grace and ſpirit, whereas thoſe that are of his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth, and ſuch as hee taketh pleaſure in, he will ſet them out in the beſt manner, and grace them with good gifts, and holie conuerſation, he will make their words gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and their miniſtery to be reuerenced in the eyes and heartes of all that feare God, they ſhall bee mightie and powerfull in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie of their meſſage, they ſhall be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the worke of the Lorde, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible in the conſciences of the wicked, they ſhall bee bleſſed in the ſtrength of the ſpirit, to turne many ſoules into the wayes of righteouſneſſe, euen ſo manie as GOD hath appointed, yea they and their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall bee a righteous generation, ouer whome the Lorde will haue a watchfull eye continually, to renewe and to repaire them with his grace and ſpirit, there ſhall not ſo ſoone any fore ſeeme to ariſe in their life, or anie corruption in their profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the Lord with his fauour and grace
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:184215:44"/>ſhall heale it againe, they ſhall be bleſſed of God to the good of Gods church which are paſtours according vnto Gods heart, and none elſe; I doe not meane ſuch as are free from all corruption and ſtaine of ſinne, for ſuch are not to bee looked for in this vale of corruption, but ſuch as the Lorde hath ſent foorth, and furniſhed with gifts, and ſanctified for the worke of his church. And the like may bee ſaide of ciuil magiſtrates, and church gouernors, that if euer the church of God reape any good by any, it is by them that are not after Antichriſts heart and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or according to the worldes approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but according to Gods wordes liking, for God bleſſeth no ordinance but his owne.</p>
            <p>This doctrine may haue a good vſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thoſe that bee Paſtours, or that haue anie publique place of teaching in the church of GOD, it maie ſeeme to admoniſh them, that they approue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues both for life and doctrine in the ſight of GOD, to bee ſuch as God liketh of, if they will doe any good in the worke of the miniſterie, and thereupon reape any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to their conſcience in the day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>There be two markes that euery miniſter approued of God muſt principally aime at, not lucre, nor gain, nor worldly promotion,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:184215:44"/>nor the vaine praiſe of the world, as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of many is, which ſhoote as rouers doe at many markes, and neuer a one certaine. But the markes that Gods miniſters muſt ſhoote at, are the glorie of God and the good of Gods church, that they may ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.1.</note> without checke of conſcience, Our hearts deſire and prayer to God is, that Iſrael may be ſaued. And ſo deere ſhould the glory of God be vnto vs, and ſo great ſhould be our loue vnto the church of God, that if it may bee aduaunced in the ſaluation of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, yea of our enemies more then in their deſtruction, we ſhoulde earneſtly craue the ſame of the Lord, yea ſo earneſtly, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Lord ſhould looſe any part of his glory therein, we ought to craue it with the hazard of our owne ſaluation, as the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> that ſingular paterne of zeale and loue did,
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.3.</note> when hee deſired to bee accurſed for his brethren ſake, the Iewes which were his brethren according to the fleſh. Some bende al their endeuor that they may be wel thought of with the Prince, or with the court, or with ſome noble man, or with the chiefe of their congregation, for wealth and authoritie, and ſome deſire only to be popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, &amp; approued of the multitude: &amp; to bring this to paſſe, they take great paines, they ſtudie hard, they reade much, they currie
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:184215:45"/>fauour with one, and flatter with another; they ſerue the time, and turne with the time, watching the tide, that they may rovve with the ſame; and if they meet with any of their brethren labouring againſt their ſtreame, him they belabour with their Inuectiues, though therein they doe ſtriue againſt the ſtreame of Gods eternall trueth; but what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re they ſo they may haue the approbation of the world, whoſe glorie they doe hunt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter like luſty <hi>Nimrods?</hi> and if they chance to miſſe of their purpoſe, as ſometimes they are croſſed as wel as others, are they not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall ſicke of <hi>Hamans</hi> diſeaſe, who was ready to die for ſorrowe, becauſe <hi>Mordecai</hi> did not bow the knee vnto him? It is a good bleſsing of God to be gracious in the eies of chriſtian Princes, and great ſtates, as it was a thing greatly to be reioyced at when <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> the Emperor of Rome embraced chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian biſhops which reſorted vnto him. And the fauour of Gods people in the Lorde is a good fauour of God, which oftentimes hee giueth vnto his ſeruants, when they ſeek not after the ſame. But yet this is not the thing that Gods ſeruants muſt affect, but all their care muſt be both at their firſt entrance into the miniſterie, and in the whole courſe of the ſame vnto the ende, that they may bee found Paſtours according to Gods owne
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:184215:45"/>heart. Both credite and maintenance in the world are the good bleſsings of the Lorde, and it ſhall be lawfull for Gods miniſters to enioy the ſame ſo farre foorth as God ſeeth good for them; but yet they muſt take heed that they make not thoſe things the ende of their worke; but that at the firſt, and at the laſt, we may be approued in the ſight of god. The apoſtle had matter of reioycing in his countrey, for he was an Iſraelite, and of his bringing vp, for hee was brought vp at the feete of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> a learned man; hee could haue ſtoode vpon his learning, for he ſpake with tongues more then any other; if others were doctors, he was a doctour of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and many great priuiledges he had that others had not. But what, doth hee ſtand ſo much to the maintenance of thoſe thinges? No,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.8.</note> he counteth them all but dung to winne Chriſt, he forgetteth them as things left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, ſo that hee may attaine vnto the marke that is ſet before him, euen the price of his high calling the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: he careth not a point for them, ſo that he may approoue himſelfe a faithfull workeman in the ſight of God. And ſo ſhoulde wee doe; if we be miniſters approoued of God, wee muſt not be as many are which make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of the word of God: but as of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie; but as of God in the ſight of God,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:184215:46"/>we muſt ſpeake in Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2-17.</note> If we be paſtors according to Gods heart, we muſt not praiſe our ſelues, nor ſtand in neede of letters of commendation vnto our charge; or of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation from them vnto others (as the Apoſtle ſaith) but our flocke muſt bee our epiſtle written in our hearts to be read and vnderſtoode of all men;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 3.1</note> not with incke, but with the ſpirit of the liuing God. If we be miniſters approoued of God, wee muſt giue no occaſion of offenſe in any thing,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 6.3.</note> that our miniſterie may be free from reproofe: But in al things (ſaith the Apoſtle) we muſt approoue our ſelues as the miniſters of god, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> in much patience, in afflictions, in neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, in diſtreſſes, in ſtripes, in priſons, in tumultes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> in labours, by watchings, by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, by puritie, by knowledge, by long ſuffering, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> by kindeneſſe, by the holi-ghoſt, by loue vnfained, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> by the worde of trueth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteouſneſſe, on the right hand and on the left, that is, both in proſperitie and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> amongſt friends and foes, by honour and diſhonour, by euill report and good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> as deceiuers, and yet true, as vnkno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and yet knovven, as dying and yet liuing, as chaſtened and yet not killed, as ſorrowing and yet alvvayes reioycing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> as poore and yet making many rich, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:184215:46"/>nothing and yet poſſeſsing all things. What a notable approbation is this? How many fellovves hath the holy Apoſtle ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> in this? This is for ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> alone, and ſuch Puritanes as he was. Heere is no mention all this while of Diſpenſations, nor of Qualifications; nor of Pluralities, nor of Vnions, nor of Totquots, nor of any ſuch implements, belike they were not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of in Saint <hi>Paules</hi> time; for if they had, ſurely the Apoſtle would not haue left them out, or it may be that they were not then in vſe, and the world is grovven wiſer now then it was in ſaint <hi>Paules</hi> time:
<q>Oh quantum mutatus ab illo!</q>
            </p>
            <p>The worlde is greatly altered ſince ſaint <hi>Paules</hi> dayes; it can no skill of ſaint <hi>Paules</hi> courſe. Well yet wee muſt learne to haue skill of it, if wee will be approoued in the ſight of God. And if all the world do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vs, and yet God condemne vs, what ſhall it aduantage vs? Moſt miſerable and wretched caitifes ſhall we prooue our ſelues to be, and better it had beene that wee had neuer beene borne, if the Lord ſhall ſay hee knoweth vs not. This was <hi>Micaiah</hi> well perſwaded of, and therefore hee ſtoode to the truth when foure hundred falſe prophets &amp; flatterers ſtood againſt him; yea when the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:184215:47"/>king and all was againſt him, but yet he was a Prophet according to the Lords heart, and that was ſufficient for him. Many at the firſt, and a great while haue made a good ſhew of great ſinceritie, that no man would haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them but to be men of God indeede (as good Prophets were called in old time) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they haue fallen by the world as <hi>Demas</hi> did, or till they haue fallen into fauour with the court, or the ſtate, or till they haue taken ſom high degree of ſchooles, or til they haue climed vp the ladder of promotion, and then the date of their zeale, and painfulnes and ſinceritie hath bin expired, and they haue turned ouer their coppy to others, &amp; hauing made ſhiprack of faith &amp; a good conſcience, they haue gone forth like <hi>Thamar</hi> out of hir brother <hi>Ammons</hi> chamber when <hi>Ammon</hi> had defloured hir, ſhe we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out with her garment of diuers colors rent &amp; torn; ſo they haue go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away with their garment of gods graces rent and torne,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 13.19.</note> onely this difference is betweene <hi>Thamar</hi> and them, ſhe wept &amp; mourned for it, and ſo doe not they, but rather reioyce at their alteration, holding theſe things nowe as moſt vile, which before the time of their ſinceritie they counted moſt precious: &amp; this is yet a moſt feareful iudgement of God vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them for their apoſtacie, for when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin thus with tongue to perſecute the trueth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:184215:47"/>which before they haue profeſſed, what doe they elſe but turne into that hie way which leadeth vnto the ſinne againſt the ſpirit of truth. And being thus reuolted from their firſt loue, they fell to be iuſt of <hi>Sauls</hi> humor, who perceiuing himſelfe to bee forſaken of the Lord for his hypocriſie, and diſſembling in Gods buſines, deſired yet of <hi>Samuel,</hi> that he might bee honoured before the elders of the people, and then he was ſafe, that was all that hee looked after. So ſay they, let vs bee honoured before the elders of the people, and that is ſufficient, for that is all that they looke after, as hauing their reward of men, and not of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <head>The third Sermon of God wooing his Church.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREMIE Chap. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 15</hi>
                     </bibl> And I will giue you Paſtors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to mine heart, which ſhall feede you with knowledge and vnderſtanding.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow the queſtion groweth how we ſhal knowe who be paſtors and miniſters according to Gods liking, and who be not. The Lord Ieſus doth beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:184215:48"/>that doubt in the 7 of <hi>Iohn</hi> ver. the 18,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b. 7.18.</note> thus; <hi>He that ſpeaketh of himſelfe ſeeketh his owne glory but he that ſeeketh his glory that ſent him, the ſame is true, and no vnrighteouſneſſe is in him:</hi> that is, hee is a true meſſenger of God, and no counterfeit. A man is ſaide to ſpeake of himſelf two waies, either when he ſpeaketh before he be required to ſpeake, or being required to ſpeake, ſpeaketh not the truth truely, but mixeth ſome deuice of his owne braine therewith: ſo did the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, for both they ranne before they were ſent, and alſo ſpake the errours of their own hart in ſtead of the word of the Lord: So did <hi>Vzzah</hi> that which he did of himſelfe, when he put his hand to the arke of the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was not called thereunto of the Lord.
<note place="margin">Ium. 23.38. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. 11.</note> So <hi>Balaam</hi> ſpake of himſelfe though he ſpake the truth without adding or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, becauſe his couetous hart which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the wages of iniquitie, made him go when the Lord bad him to ſtay When <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> profecied of Chriſts death, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith; <hi>This ſpake he not of himſelfe,</hi> that is, he did not inuent it of his own brain. But what is it for a miniſter to ſeek his own glory?
<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.51.</note> to be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the ſtain of vainglory? no, for <hi>Paul</hi> was infected with that ſtaine, as appeares by his own teſtimony; for therefore hee had a meſſenger of Sathan ſent to humble him,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.7.</note>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:184215:48"/>leſt he ſhould be lifted vp out of meaſure for thoſe heauenly reuelations which were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto him. What then? to extoll his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie and calling when iuſt occaſion ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth? no neither, for the Apoſtle hauing to deale with ſuch as went about to abuſe his miniſtery. He extolleth his miniſtery in this maner;
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.5.</note> Verely I ſuppoſe that I was not infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the very chiefe apoſtles. But then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed doth he ſeeke his owne glory, when he preacheth mans doctrine to pleaſe men.
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>For now, preach I mans doctrine or Gods?</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>or go I about to pleaſe men? for if I ſhould yet pleaſe men, I were not the ſeruant of Chriſt I certifie you brethren that the Goſpell which was preached of me, was not after man.</hi> And the apoſtle cha. 4. ver. 17. deſcribes the vaineglorious falſe apoſtles by this marke, that they would exclude all others as no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that the people might altogether affect them. <hi>But what is it to ſeek Gods glory?</hi>
               <note place="margin">4.17.</note> that is a very needful queſtion indeed; <hi>what is it to ſay God be praiſed, or, thanks be to God?</hi> No, for ſo did the proud Phariſy who was compoun ded of vaineglory;
<note place="margin">Luke. 18.</note> and when he pronounced thoſe wordes, ſought nothing leſſe then the glory of God, and nothing more then his owne glorie. What then? is it to ſay, Let God be glorified? No neither, for ſo did the perſecutors of gods church when they exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:184215:49"/>their brethren, as appeareth in <hi>Eſay</hi> 66.5. like the Prelates, who beganne all their excommunications and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with <hi>In nomine Dei;</hi> and ſo <hi>In nomine Dei</hi> burned, and impriſoned, and maſſacred many of the deare ſaints and ſeruaunts of God. And like vnto the former are the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who in all their idolatrous and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious ſeruices ſing, Glory be to the father, to the Sonne, and to the Holi-ghoſt, &amp;c. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which do giue as much glory to God, as the Iewes did vnto Chriſt, when they ſpit in his face, and ſaluted him with the knee, crying, Haile King of the Iewes. What then? to ſpeake Gods will without adding or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 23.12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. 2.16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.</note> No neither; for ſo much did <hi>Balaam,</hi> who for al that, ſought nothing but his own commoditie and gaine, and therefore is ſaid to ſerue for the wages of iniquitie. Howe then? To come in outward humilitie, and ſhewes of holineſſe, as to profeſſe wilfull pouertie, to goe barefooted, &amp;c. after the monkiſh manner of the Popiſh friers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that fraternitie? Nothing leſſe; for the apoſtle doth vtterly diſclaime them, and maruelleth that they which are dead with Chriſt from the ordinaunces of the worlde, will bee burned againe with traditions,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.20.</note> as though they liued in the world, and not in Chriſt; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> as, touch not, taſte not, handle not,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:184215:49"/>which all periſh with the vſing, and are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the commaundements and doctrines of men: Which things haue a ſhewe of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (ſaith the apoſtle) in voluntarie religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and humbleneſſe of minde, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> and in not ſparing the body, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> neither haue they it in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eſtimation to ſatiſfie the fleſh: thus the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of mens traditions, to teach vs that we muſt thinke of them but as of burdens too heauy for the conſciences of chriſtians to beare, and ſhewes, without any ſubſtance they are in the ſight of God. How then doth Gods miniſter ſeeke the glory of God? Firſt, in ſpeaking; then marke his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Secondly, in liuing; then marke his life: for the firſt it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.18.</note> he ſpeaketh not of himſelfe; for the ſecond, it is ſaid, there is no vnrighteouſneſſe in him, that is, hee is not a ſubiect to ſinne and wickedneſſe. Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit and falſe apoſtles are deceitfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.13.</note> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) &amp; can tranſforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and no maruell (ſaith hee) for Sathan himſelfe is tranſformed into an Angel of light. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no great thing, though his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters tranſforme themſelues as though they were the miniſters of righteouſneſſe. But <hi>ex fructibus,</hi> by their fruits, (ſaith the Lorde Ieſus) you ſhall know them.
<note place="margin">Math. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The ſorcerers and ſoothſaiers of Egypt did imitate, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:184215:50"/>counterfeit <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in many things, ſo doe the miniſters of the deuill counterfeit the miniſters of God in many things: but as <hi>Moſes</hi> did one thing which the ſorcerers could not do; ſo Gods meſſenger doth one thing the other cannot doe; that is, they ſeeke the glorie of him that ſent them. Now when the people ſaw <hi>Moſes</hi> do that which all the cunning men of Egypt could not do, they ſaid; this is the finger of GOD: ſo when men ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſee a man ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in his whole miniſterie nothing but the glorie of GOD that ſent him, they muſt needes ſaie, This is a miniſter of God.</p>
            <p>In the doctrine it will appeare two waies; Firſt, by the matter deliuered; ſecondly, by the manner of deliuering. For the matter, it ſhalbe ſuch as God hath put into his mouth, that he may ſay as the apoſtle did, <hi>That which I haue receiued of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 11, 23.</note> 
               <hi>I haue deliuered vnto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>and if an angell from heauen ſhall preach otherwiſe then the apoſtle preached, he is to be accurſed.</hi> And herein he is not to holde himſelfe ſufficiently diſcharged, if hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth ſome part of Gods will, and leaueth out ſome part thereof, but he is to deliuer to the church of God, the whole counſell of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 20, 20.27.</note> as time and occaſion ſerueth; and yet in ſuch ſort as ſhall bee moſt profitable for the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:184215:50"/>people, for wiſedome and faithfulneſſe muſt waite one vppon another in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God. And ſtill hee is to meete with ſuch things as obſcure the glorie of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> did when he came to Athens,
<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> &amp; percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them to be addicted to idolatry and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, he aduanceth the true God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſeth al falſe gods, &amp; that he doth 2. waies. Firſt, by ſetting forth in God his power,
<note place="margin">24, 25, 28, 30.</note> his goodnes &amp; his prouidence; ſecondly, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the vanitie of idols, &amp; the ignorance of the Athenians. Againe, the manner is to be obſerued; and that our doctrine may win glorie to him that ſent vs, two things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: Firſt, concealement of humane skil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecondly, demonſtration of the ſpirit; both which are euident in the example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles preaching, who may bee a patterne of true preaching to all the doctours in the worlde.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> VVhen I came vnto you brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren (ſaith hee) I came not with excellencie of wordes, or of wiſedome, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſhewing vnto you the teſtimonie of God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for I eſteemed not to knowe anie thing among you, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Ieſus Chriſt, and him crucified. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And I was among you in weakeneſſe, and in feare, and in much trembling. Neither ſtoode my worde, and my preaching, in the intiſing ſpeech of mans wiſedome, but in plaine euidence of the ſpirit, and of power.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:184215:51"/>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> drift is to reproue certaine teachers at Corinth: but for what? not for hereſie, but for the manner of their teaching, and in that for two things, for humane eloquence, and wiſedome, neither are they ſimplie reprooued for theſe, for they are good in their place, but becauſe they made a ſhew of them in declaring of Gods meſſage. And in the fourth verſe, humane wiſedome is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the euidence of the ſpirit, to ſhew that they which ſtudie only for humane learning and eloquence, cannot preach in the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and power of the ſpirit. And this he prooueth by many arguments. Firſt, the doctrine that I taught was Gods will and teſtament, <hi>ergo,</hi> I muſt not vtter it in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and forme after men, but it muſt bee ſhewed as hee ſet it forth. Secondly, in the ſecond verſe, <hi>I haue purpoſed to know nothing but Ieſus Chriſt and him crucified;</hi> that is, to profeſſe nothing elſe, for hee could not but know many things more, therefore the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all humane wiſedome was to bee laid aſide. Thirdly, in the third verſe, hee ſaith, it was in much weakeneſſe, feare, and trembling, becauſe hee was to deale with the deuill, and with men of beaſtly condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who could not be ſubdued with gallant ſhewes of humane ſtrength, nor with flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and flouriſhing in humane eloquence &amp;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:184215:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>wiſedome. Fourthly, in the 5. verſe he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a notable reaſon why it was thus, and why it muſt be thus; leſt your faith ſhoulde ſtand vppon mans wiſedome, rather then in the power of God, and ſo man ſhoulde haue the glorie of conuerting mens ſoules to the faith, which is proper to God only: therfore, in the miniſterie the power of God muſt only be ſhewed in demonſtration of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and of power. Fiftly,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> we haue this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in earthen veſſelles, that the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of that power, might bee of God, and not of vs. The miniſter is compared to a veſſell, and a homely one, hee ſheweth a treaſure in it: Whatſoeuer therefore is in man muſt be hidden: that when the treaſure worketh, the vertue which is of God, may be aſcribed vnto God, and not to man. But then it will be demaunded of ſome, what vſe there is of arts, of doctors, and fathers, and the tougues, if they may not be ſhewed &amp; alleaged in the publique miniſterie of the word. To whom we may anſwere, that as thoſe things are the good bleſsings of god on his church ſo there is a priuate vſe of them in ſtudy, to helpe the man of God to find out doctrine and to ſet it forth, but in publike they are not to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the teſtimony of the apoſtle, except it be in diſputations and controuerſies againſt thoſe that rely vpon them as the papiſts do.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:184215:52"/>
            <p> As there muſt bee a concealement of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane eloquence and wiſedome, ſo there muſt bee a demonſtration of the ſpirite,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirit.</note> as the Apoſtle ſheweth in the fourth verſe of the ſecond chapter and the firſt epiſtle to the Corinthians, and that is, when the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſo deliuereth the word, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may perceiue, it is not hee that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, but the ſpirite of God in him. The whole foureteenth chapter of the firſt epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corinthians,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 14.</note> is a commentarie of this point, and in the foure and twentieth verſe he ſheweth, that if there be propheci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is expounding, and applying to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4.</note> the ſcripturs in a knowen tongue: if an idiot, or an vnbeleeuer come in the meane time he is rebuked, and iudged of al, that is, he ſhall take himſelfe ſo to be, for the ſecrets of his hart ſhalbe made manifeſt, and ſo he will fall downe and worſhip God, and ſay plainely, that God is in you indeede. And thus muſt men prophecie to worke this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.8.</note> they muſt bee as <hi>Michaiah</hi> was, full of power, by the ſpirit of the Lorde, and of iudgement and of ſtrength, to declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Iacob his tranſgreſsion, and to Iſrael his ſinne. The Apoſtles were not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to witneſſe of Chriſt, till they hadde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſpirite that muſt execute it. And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſecond of the Actes it is ſayde, that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:184215:52"/>it lighted on them like fiery tongues, to ſhew that the ſpirit of GOD maketh the ſpeech to burne. Then whereſoeuer the ſpeech toucheth, it burneth by the outward ſigne, the inward worke is ſignified by all which we may ſee that there muſt be no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the perſon, but of the power of the ſpirit. And further, becauſe explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the verie ſoule of the ſpirit, therefore that eſpecially muſt bee laboured for; for in man is ſoule, and bodie, and ſpirit.
<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.2</note> The ſoule giueth life. The ſpirite liuelineſſe; and is the moouing and ſtirring of the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. The doctrine muſt alſo haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, or elſe it is dead; now when it is applied by the ſpirit, it is moſt liuely and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall.</p>
            <p>The liuelineſſe and power of the worde thus preached, appeareth in this demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration. Take a thing that is redde hote, and lay it to another thing that is colde, and it ſhall kindle a heate in that too. So the miniſters tongue is a fierie tongue,
<note place="margin">Simile.</note> novve when it is brought to mans ſences and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, it worketh the like heate in them, ſo that the power of the ſpirite is conueyed vnto them. And thus an impreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made in the heartes of the people. And when the man ſeeth this, he falleth downe, hee glorifieth GOD, and reuerenceth the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:184215:53"/>miniſter, &amp; God in him. And for the better procuring and preſeruing of this reuerence: it is verie requiſite alſo, that his meſſage bee deliuered with authoritie and maieſtie, as <hi>Paul</hi> aduiſeth <hi>Titus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.4.</note> the reaſon is in the 2. Cor. 3.20. The miniſter is an embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor for Chriſt; now the embaſſador beareth his perſon that ſent him, hee is his vicegerent to ſpeake and do that that he himſelfe doth; therefore the whole function muſt bee with authority.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 7.28, 29.</note> It is ſaid that the people were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonied at Chriſts doctrin, becauſe he taught them as one hauing authority, and not as the Scribes, to ſhew that the miniſter ſhall neuer moue by his doctrine, except it be with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. He that wil approue himſelfe in the ſight of God to be a miniſter after the Lords liking, and win glory to him that ſent him, muſt haue his life clothed with robes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and righteouſnes. I mean not that a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life is eſſentiall to a miniſter, ſo that he is no miniſter that wants it, but that it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for a miniſter, for many ſhall ſay at the laſt day to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 7.22.</note> 
               <hi>Wee haue propheſied in thy name;</hi> to whom anſwere ſhalbe made againe, <hi>depart from me ye workers of iniquitie I know you not.</hi> The neceſsitie of it may appeare by many reaſons: firſt, a miniſter vnleſſe hee bee ſanctified hee ſhall neuer ſoundely, and liuely vnderſtand the word of GOD;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5, 9.</note> for
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:184215:53"/>the Lorde reuealeth his will vnto the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his counſelles vnto them that feare him, and to none elſe. Lawyers become cunning by long reading; and Phiſitions by experience; yet no man was euer a perfect, found, and iudiciall diuine without holines. This knowledge is rather feeling, then lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in aboundance of beart, rather then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſtudie, ſent by God to good men: ſo that, hee that can ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.117</note> 
               <hi>I loue thy lawe,</hi> may ſay, <hi>I haue more vnderstanding then my teachers.</hi> It is the equitie of God, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to obey, vnwoorthy to knowe; for what ſhould hee do with a talent which wil not vſe it? Therefore he which forbiddeth pearles to ſwine, ſtaies his hand from caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowledge to the wicked, except ſo much as ſhall condemne them. Further, the ignorant people cannot ſee the ordinance of God, but they vſe to iudge of a mans mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery by ſenſible things which they ſee in him; therefore a good life is neceſſarie in a miniſter. For they ſay, becauſe he liueth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his teaching wee will heare him, as <hi>Herod</hi> heard <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 6.20.</note> becauſe he was a good man and a godly. If teachers of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane artes ſhall tell generall things without examples, it is hard to learne of them: ſo if teachers of diuine things ſhall teach onely without examples, it wil be as hard to learn
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:184215:54"/>of them; therefore the miniſter muſt ſet a copie with his life, which the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> requireth when hee ſaieth,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. 5.2, 3</note> 
               <hi>Feede the flocke of God, which dependeth on you, caring for it, not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready minde, not as though ye were Lordes ouer Gods heritage, but that ye may be enſamples of the flocke.</hi> VVhat manner of examples miniſters muſt bee. Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſheweth, 1 Timothie. 4.12. when hee ſaieth, <hi>Bee vnto them that beleeue an enſample, in worde, in conuerſation, in loue, in ſpirite, in faith, and in pureneſſe.</hi> It is ſaid vnto all men, Be ye holy; but it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned the miniſter more ſpecially. to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned both with inward and outward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. Inward holineſſe ſtandeth in faith and a good conſcience, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> would haue to be in <hi>Timothie,</hi> as wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons,
<note place="margin">Tim. 1.19.</note> without which he cannot fight a good fight; the firſt is, a perſwaſion of the trueth, or true doctrine: the other excuſeth a man in euery action,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron. 15.15,</note> and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a good conſcience a continuall feaſt. And <hi>Paul</hi> laboured to keepe that aboue all things;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 24.16.</note> 
               <hi>for I endeuour my ſelfe to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a cleare conſcience both towards God, and towards men.</hi> Outward holines which muſt be in the miniſter of God, is ſet foorth in I. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>A Biſhop must be vnreprooueable.</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:184215:54"/>Againe, there be outward dueties required of him, in regard of his perſon. in regard of his familie, in regarde of his calling, and in regard of ſtrangers. Firſt in regarde of his owne perſon, he muſt be vnblameable, ſo farre from outward crimes, and groſe ſinnes, that hee muſt bee free from all iuſt cauſe of ſuſpition, becauſe he muſt reforme others; not to be free from ſinne, for that is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in this life. Hee muſt wiſely conceale his infirmities from others, for being once knowen, they are as a barre caſt in the way of the people to ſtumble at. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer great and foule faultes in an other man ſeeme to bee but ſmall, yet euery light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie in the miniſter is accompted as a plague-ſore running vppon him, the which maketh him to be abhorred of the profane and ignorant ſort: therefore if the miniſter ſhoulde make his infirmities knowen vnto them, it were all one as if hee ſhoulde ſay, I haue the plague about me, and ſo make them to abhorre both his perſon, and his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regarde of his ovvne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it is required that hee be the husband of one wife, for in thoſe times men had twoo wiues, and then he might not be a miniſter, becauſe that hee hadde broken the holie ordinaunce of almightie God in himſelfe,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:184215:55"/>which ſhould ſee it kept in others. If hee had bin ſuch a one, and now is ſingle, or ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned onely to one, hee may be a chriſtian, but not a miniſter. And the like is to be ſaid of him that hath been ſometime a Preacher of the goſpell, and after that fell to be an ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later or a Popiſh prieſt, and is now a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the goſpel again; the church may vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his repentance take him for a chriſtian, but hee ought not to ſerue in the publique miniſterie of the word, as yet many doe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is not onely blemiſhed himſelfe worſe then a man that wanteth a member, which in no wiſe might ſerue in the worke of the miniſtery, but alſo is a fowle ſcarre in the face of the church, which muſt be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that the church may looke with a loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and comely countenance, that her friends may be in loue with hir, and not through hir vgly and deformed viſage, be occaſioned to loathe her: and this is that which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> in plaine words hath recorded in this manner,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>zech. 44, 10,</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, No ſtranger vncircumciſed in heart, nor vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in fleſh, ſhal enter into my ſanctuarie: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Leuites that are gone backe from mee, when Iſrael went aſtray, which went aſtray from me after their idolles, but they ſhall beare their iniquitie.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
               <hi>And they ſhal ſerue in my ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, and keepe the gates of the houſe, and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:184215:55"/>in the houſe.</hi> [But how ſhal they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter?] they ſhall ſlay the <hi>burnt offering and the ſacrifice for the people, and they ſhall ſtand before them to ſerue them:</hi> that is, they ſhall ſerue as drudges to doe all the ſeruile worke that belongs to the ſanctuarie, like the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites, who were appointed by <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to carry wood and draw water; and why?
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 9.27.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſerued before, their idolles, and cauſed the houſe of Iſrael to fall into iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;
<note place="margin">Ezech. 44.12,</note> 
               <hi>Therefore haue</hi> I <hi>lift vp mine hand againſt them</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>and they ſhal beare their iniquitie.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
               <hi>And they ſhall not come neere vnto me, to do the office of the prieſt vnto me, neither ſhal they come nere vnto any of mine holy things in the moſt holy place, but they ſhall beare their ſhame, and their abominations which they haue committed. And</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> I <hi>will make them keepers of the watch of the houſe, for all the ſeruice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and for all that ſhal be done therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any man will obiect againſt this that hath been ſpoken, that <hi>Paul</hi> was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuter of the goſpell, and yet afterward was caled to be a preacher of the goſpel, he may; but it will not ſerue his turne; for firſt, <hi>Paul</hi> was not a preacher before he was a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for then had hee beene a right apoſtata, or backe-ſlider from the faith, as thoſe men were of whom I ſpake before, as namely, ſuch as were preachers and profeſſors of the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:184215:56"/>goſpel in king <hi>Edwards</hi> dayes, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the goſpel in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, &amp; then to become preachers of the goſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in Qu. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes; ſuch Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes Imeane was <hi>Paul</hi> neuer, neither are they to be admitted into the miniſterie nowe. Secondly, <hi>Paul</hi> was extraordinarily called and conuerted; it doth not therefore follow that any now-adays ſhould looke for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rdinary calling, when the ſame Apoſtle hath laied down an ordinarie rule, for an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie miniſterie, and amongſt other rules hath laide downe this for one, that a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter muſt be vnrep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooueable: but it is verie euident, that ſuch apoſtates and runningates from the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rh (which haue made alſo others to fall away with them) are very inſtly to be reprooued. Thirdly, it is required of a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God, that he be watchfull, becauſe the church of God is ſubiect to the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of heretikes, and Sathan, therefore he muſt of neceſsity be reſident vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his charge, that he may be acquainted with the natures, and conditions, &amp; opinions of his flock con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, &amp; ſo meet with euery inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as it ariſeth before it grow to a head <hi>Curſed is he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 48.10.</note> If negligence in the Lordes worke be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<note place="margin">Non-reſidencie.</note> then what bleſsing can a Non-reſident look for vpon his non-reſidencie? for there
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:184215:56"/>can be no greater negligence in doing of the Lords work, then for a miniſter to leaue his place &amp; ſtanding, wherein god hath ſet him, and to commit the care ouer vnto a hireling which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to him, like the vnkind nurſe which turneth ouer the childe to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whom the parents of the childe neuer truſted withall. If any wil ſay they can be but taught, &amp; as good by one as by another, they do but deceiue themſelues. For if the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſhould commit their owne child to a nurſe, whom they haue made choice of before an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, they would not like it well, nor take it well if that nurſe ſhould take her wages, and poſt it ouer to another, and ſay, it can be but kept, or, it can be but fed, and as good by one as by another. Beſides that, the Lord in his word expreſly condemneth ſuch kind of dealing in the prieſts of Iſrael,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 44.</note> charging the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue broken his couenant; and How? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had brought in ſtrangers to pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the houſe of God, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> being vocircumciſed in fleſh, and in heart, who offered with the bread, fat and bloud, which the Lord calleth abominations; ſhewing the reaſon of it, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>for ye haue not kept the ordinaunces of mine holie things, but you your ſelues haue ſet others to take the charge of my ſanctuarie;</hi> which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as directly againſt Non-reſidents and their Curates or ſubſtitutes as can be; for if
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:184215:57"/>ſuch care was required of the Leuites and prieſtes vnder the ceremonies of the lawe, which were but ſhadowes of Chriſt and the goſpel. How much more ought the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the goſpel to haue this care to looke vnto the worke of God themſelues, vnto whome is committed, not the ſhadowes, but the ſubſtance it ſelfe, euen the Son of God, who was the ende of thoſe ceremoniall fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and ſhadowes, and the diſpenſation of the goſpel of Chriſt, wherein is exhibited more cleerely vnto the church of God euen Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe alredy come, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and in heauen glorified, which faire exceedeth al thoſe things which were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the prieſts and Leuites: which did alſo exhibite Chriſt vnto the church, but more obſcurely, and a farre off. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f God would not diſpenſe with them for commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the charge of his houſe then, to others, much leſſe wil he diſpenſe with vs for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the charge of his houſe nowe, to others. And admit that their ſubſtitutes be honeſt men, godly, learned, and painefull too, which yet is but ſeldome (though ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time) ſeene, if they be not troubled, nor cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into queſtion as others be, yet wee muſt know that God hath not promiſed any bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but to the labours of ſuch as he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and ſet ouer his people, and not ouer
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:184215:57"/>euerie hireling, for God will bleſſe no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance but his owne, what care and intent ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer men haue.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is required of a miniſter, that he be ſober, that is, there muſt bee a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all his affections, and of al his appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, as in eating and drinking, in apparrell, in recreation, in companie keeping, and ſuch like, vnto which muſt be ioyned mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, that in good and ſeemely order, his outwarde behauiour muſt not be offenſiue, he muſt be free from all light ſpeeches, or ſhewes, hee muſt learne to beare his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon orderly, in dignitie and grauitie, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the miniſter of God: It is alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that hee bee harborous and full of hoſpitalitie, according to his abilitie, and an entertainer of the faithfull; hee muſt be alſo apt to teach, &amp; able to deliuer the word, and to apply it aptly and fitly, according to time, place, perſons, and al occaſions, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, he had a tongue to ſpeake words in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<note place="margin">Eſa, 50.4;</note> which as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) are like aples of golde with pictures of ſiluer,
<note place="margin">Pro. 25.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> moſt precious and comely, whereof one is worth a thouſand of others, &amp; hath more grace then ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. There be three foule vices, which muſt be remoued from his perſon. Firſt hee muſt not be giuen to wine, that is, alwaies to ſit by it, as they that take pleſure in it, like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:184215:58"/>cannot eate, but ſtil muſt haue wine. <hi>Timothy</hi> might d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nke wine, not for pleaſure, but for his helth, &amp; for pleſure too, ſo it be not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily. Secondly, he muſt be no ſtriker, if he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ouercom his people by exhortation, &amp; inſtruction in his publike function, hee may not ſtrike them. In his family he may ſtrike his ſeruants and his children when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue correction, yet with diſcretion, for ther he is both miniſter and maſter. And in wars alſo he may ſtrike the enemie, when by the magiſtrate hee ſhall be thereunto lawfully called, for hee is both a miniſter and a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. Thirdly, he muſt not bee giuen to filthy lucre, as they that liue of the gain of vſury; or of cards and dice, and other gaming, or by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gains that come by hooke or by crook (as the prouerbe goeth) againſt the law of God &amp; man. The reaſons are taken from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie cauſes, for ſtrokes come from anger, &amp; he muſt bee a man that can bridle his anger: and couetouſnes is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he cauſe of filthy lucre, as it is the roote of all euill, which muſt not be in the man of God.</p>
            <p>It is required of Gods miniſter in reſpect of his family,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uries in reſpect of his family.</note> he be ſuch a one that can go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uern his family wel. For the gouernment of a family is a great ſtay of a church, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, that is, when by the example of the miniſter others gouerne wel, yet there is
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:184215:58"/>ſufficient doctrine in the word to gouern by. Then doth the miniſter gouerne wel, when his whole family is in ſubiection, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the magiſtrate, and willing to ſuffer when they offend: now if any looke for liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is children; therfore the apoſtle putteth children for all, &amp; ſaith that they muſt be in ſubiection; therfore much more ſeruants: &amp; that this may not ſeem a ſmal matter, he ſaith that it maſt be in al honeſty, or com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines, to ſhewe that there is decen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie in that family, when euery childe doth his duety, and great comelines is in ſubiection; the reaſon is, if a man cannot rule his own family, how can he rule Gods church? therefore he is not a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter after the Lords heart, that bringeth vp his children diſſolutely: and here by the way we may ſee, that God doth not require of the miniſter either a ſingle life, or a monkiſh life nor a whoriſh, &amp; adulterous life, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo leadeth in popery is better accepted then he that liueth in holy eſtate of matrimony.
<note place="margin">In reſpect of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> calling to the faith.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In regard of his calling to the faith it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that he be not a yong pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or a nouice, gods church is compared to a vineyard thoſe which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted are as it were brought out of the field &amp; planted in the vineyard: now if if theſe be but as of a years growth or ſo, they are not fit to be miniſters, leſt they being puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp (as many are) fal into temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:184215:59"/>A man newely conuerted, hath not ſounde knowledge, &amp; ſo falleth by ignorance of his mind to error, and ſo to hereſie by pride, and ſo is in the ſame ſin with the deuill: nay, the apoſtle ſaith, in the condemnation of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, that is, to be without a ſauior, or not to be ſaued: therefore we ought to take heede, for the danger is great, pride and liking of hart, wil bring a man to the diuils ſin; if it puffe vs vp, then are we gone; pride keepeth out hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which muſt needs receiue Chriſt. He that can aſcribe confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to himſelf, keepeth out pride, or at the leaſt fighteth againſt it.</p>
            <p>The laſt property that is required to be in a miniſter,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſpect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngers.</note> is in reſpect of ſtrangers. He muſt haue a good teſtimony of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, euen of infidels, who are not yet conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So he muſt behaue himſelfe, that euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked (if it be poſsible) he may haue a good report. Hee muſt be curteous to all, good, and bad, not curteous to the faithful, &amp; auſtere to the wicked, but curteous to al: the reaſon is, leſt he fal into reproch, &amp; the ſnare of the deuil. The reſon of this duty is drawn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inconuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that wil folow the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; for whom muſt hee conuert? the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: then if he come into hatred with them, hee ſhall be able to do them no good, if they blaſpheme God and him. And thus by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch, hee is caſt into the ſnares of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:184215:59"/>either to be diſſolute, &amp; not to care what he doth, or elſe deſperate of verie griefe and ſorrow of heart: by which we may ſee what danger it is to raiſe vp ſlander of any man: it is as much as a mans ſoule is worth, for this giueth the deuill occaſion to worke vpon a man. And a man may ſpeake that which may make an other man come to deſtruction, ſo much as lieth in him that ſo ſpeaketh. The world is a place where ſatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath al ſnares on ech ſide, therefore we muſt take heed. They that lie in the ſnares, it may be, ſee nothing of all this, but thoſe who haue bin in, and are gone out, doe ſee them, therfore it is needfull to pray, <hi>Leade vs not into temptation, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from euill.</hi> And thus much for the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and qualities of a miniſter in reſpect of his own perſon, of his family, of his calling to the faith, and of ſtrangers, by which (togither with that which hath beene ſaide of his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine) it may eaſily appeare who be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters according to the Lords heart or liking, and who be not: It followeth in the text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which ſhal feede you with knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> Now the Lord ſheweth what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit they ſhàl reape by their paſtors, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge and vnderſtanding; they ſhall not only be to Gods liking, but alſo for their ſoules good: nay, they cannot be paſtours to Gods liking, except they be alſo for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:184215:60"/>of Gods people; for God liketh well, when his church th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ueth wel, &amp; the church thriueth wel when it groweth in knowledge and vnderſtanding; for that is the way to grow ſtrong in faith &amp; repentance, &amp; loue, and in zeale, and in patience and in al the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing graces of the ſpirit of God, to know and to vnderſtand the waies of the Lord. This knowledge is the knowlege of Gods wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in his worde, which ſheweth both what his purpoſe is concerning all men, both good and bad, wicked and godly, the faithful and vnfaithfull, the elect and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, the ſaluation of the one, and the damnation of the other, the aſſurance of both, the meanes and the cauſes of both. It ſheweth alſo what is required of al men to be beleeued, &amp; what to be practiſed, for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of his glory. This is called the knowledge of God in Chriſt Ieſus, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſtandeth eternall life, <hi>Iohn</hi> chapter ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene verſe 3. This knowledge of God is the firſt and chiefeſt principle in chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, becauſe without it, it is not poſsible for any man to worſhip him, as he ought to bee worſhipped of vs, for the Apoſtle ſaith, how ſhall we call on him, on whom we haue not beleeued? and how can we beleeue in him, of whom we haue not heard? and how ſhall we heare without a preacher?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.14.</note> as if hee ſhoulde
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:184215:60"/>ſay, we can doe none of theſe things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge; for knowledge is the end of hearing and of preaching: therefore doe we preach and heare, not to make the ſcriptures better (as ſome ſenceleſſe idiots doe imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine) but to bring men to the knowledge of the truth. Now as the apoſtle ſpeaketh of faith and prayer, which bee twoo eſpeciall parts of Gods worſhip, wee can neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue aright, nor pray aright without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo may it bee ſaide of feare and loue, and all other points of the true worſhip and ſeruice of God, that men can neither feare God aright, nor loue God aright, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes him aright, nor acknowledge his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aright, without the knowledge of thoſe things.</p>
            <p>And for the better bringing vp of men in this holy knowledge of God, the Lorde hath giuen his ſtatutes vnto <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his ordinaunces vnto <hi>Iſraell,</hi> which hee hath not vouchſafed vppon all nations, for the heathen haue not the knoledge of his waies; Pſalme a hundred fortie and ſix. And theſe ſtatutes of God are contained in the bookes of the olde and new Teſtament called the holie Scriptures, by the waie of excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which being rightly vnderſtoode of vs doe bring vs directly to the true knowledge of God, and of our ſelues. And becauſe there
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:184215:61"/>are in the ſcriptures ſom things that be hard and darke to our vnderſtanding: therefore the Lord hath ordained paſtors &amp; doctors, whome hee hath alſo furniſhed with giftes of knowledge and vtterance, and learning, and ſanctification, that they may teach the Lords people the true meaning of the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and ſo traine them vp in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and obedience of the Lord.</p>
            <p>By this then it appeareth how neceſſarie it is for all Gods children to haue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of GOD, the vnderſtanding of the ſcriptures, and the preaching of the word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them by a painefull, faithfull, and learned miniſterie. And on the other ſide, it be wrayeth the peſtilent daunger of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ignorant miniſters, and alſo the barrenneſſe of bare reading, without the til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of expounding, of catechiſing, of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, of exhortation, and of application, the which is the life of doctrine; by which holy meanes, as it were, with the Lords ploughs the fallow groundes of mens hearts are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4.4.</note> whereas otherwiſe the ſeede is but caſt amongſt the thornes, as <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeakes. When the Queen of Ethiopia her chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine was reading the prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> in his chariot,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.30.</note> 
               <hi>Philip</hi> asked him if he vnderſtoode what he read, to ſhew that a man may reade and reade againe, and bee neuer the nearer
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:184215:61"/>without an interpreter, as that noble man confeſſed; for how can I vnderſtand (ſaide he) without a guide? Therefore <hi>Ezra</hi> (when he had read the ſcripture,) he alſo gaue the ſence,
<note place="margin">Nehem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.</note> and cauſed the people to vnderſtand the reading, to ſhew, that bare reading is not ſufficient to bring men to vnderſtanding. And therefore our ſauior Chriſt alſo, when hee had read a place of <hi>Eſay</hi> that concerned himſelfe, hee cloſed vp the booke,
<note place="margin">Luke 4.20.</note> and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the text, making application thereof to his hearers: whereuppon it followeth in the ſame place, that all that heard him bare him witnes, and wondred at the gracious words that proceeded out of his mouth, to ſhewe, that preaching giueth grace to reading. And when the word read is opened, and applied, then men beare witneſſe of the trueth, that is, they knowe what to holde and beleeue for trueth, and not before. This the apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> knew very well, and therefore hee did not onely teach the Epheſians openly, but priuately alſo in euery houſe, going from houſe to houſe, warning,
<note place="margin">Act. 20.20, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and exhorting eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one as hee had occaſion, to ſhewe what courſe thoſe ſheepeheardes muſt take that would bring their flocks vnto the green pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of heauenly comforts, and the liuing waters of eternall happineſſe, both growing and flouring out of the liuely fountaines of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:184215:62"/>knowledge and vnderſtanding in the holy word of God. And further, for the neceſsity of knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding, what could the lord ſay more to ſhew the greatnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then to call them by the name of foode, or meate and drinke, for ſo he doth; I <hi>will giue you paſtors, which ſhal feed you with knowledge and vnderſtanding;</hi> as if knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding were foode of the ſoule, and ſo they be to teach vs; as there is nothing more neceſſary for the ſtrengthning of the bodie, then meate and drinke, ſo there is nothing more neceſſarie for the ſauing of the ſoule then knowledge and vnderſtanding. Take away from the bodie ordinary ſuſtenance long, and it ſtarueth. And take away know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtanding from the ſoule, and it periſheth: Therefore as Chriſt ſaid when he raiſed vp <hi>Iairus</hi> daughter, giue hir meate, ſo the Lorde ſaieth, when the ſoule is raiſed vp to the life of God; giue it meate; but that muſt be knowledge and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Againe, as knowledge and vnderſtanding are here called food, ſo paſtors are called fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as if they were nurſes, &amp; the people as babes &amp; children, which neither know what is good for them, nor howe to dreſſe their meat nor how to feed themſelues. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many doe not vnfitly compare the bare reading of the ſcripture vnto a whole loafe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:184215:62"/>ſet before children, which muſt bee cutte in peeces, and be d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uided before it can profite them. The preachers are alſo called feeders, to ſhew that they muſt be like nurſes in abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, in affection and diſcretion. Some haue wherewith to feede their children, but they are vnkind and vnnaturall, like cruel harlots that kill their children, that they may not be troubled with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Some beare a good affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their children, but their breaſtes are drie, and they haue no meate to giue them when they crie for it; as in the great famine of Samaria. Som haue wherwith to feed, but for want of diſcretion to obſerue the childes nature and conſtitution, as alſo the weaknes, or ſtrongnes of the ſtomack, the frowardnes &amp; tendernes of thinfant, and the cauſes of al, it happeneth that much is giuen, and little digeſted, &amp; great pain is taken to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, bicauſe the child is either miſdieted or diſtempred, or handled too tenderly, or too rigorouſly. Therefore in the feeders of the ſoule there ought to bee ſufficient ſtore of knowlege, there ought to be a louing &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affection, tempered with wiſedome and diſcretion, that euery one may haue his due portion faithfully diſtributed vnto him, and that in due time and ſeaſon. It is a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearing to heare the children crie for bread, and it ſhal be anſwered againe by the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:184215:63"/>Nurſe, I haue none for thee, thou muſt ſtarue, for I haue none to giue thee. But it is a thouſand times more lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table to heare the ſoules mone for want of ſpiritual foode, oh what accompt haue they to make vnto God that take the place of ſpirituall nurſes, and haue no milke in their breaſts, that is, know nothing to any purpoſe? is it nothing to ſtarue the Lordes people? Is the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of mens ſoules no ſin before the Lorde? O that the ſmoky <hi>Kemarius</hi> of this our age, as vnpreaching miniſters and non-reſidents, and ſuch like did conſider well of this point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then would they not leaue their occupations and trades, as many haue done, and betake them to the miniſterie, as their laſt refuge, for liuing and maintenaunce ſake, but they would leaue the miniſterie as faſt: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelues to ſome other trade of life againe, and wiſh that their heades were fountaines of teares, that they might weep day and night for the ſlaughter and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they haue made of the Lordes people. VVhich they were better to doe nowe while the Lorde doeth allot them a time of repentance, then heereafter in hell, from whence there is no redemption. Oh that our Patrons, and Biſhops likewiſe did enter into the due conſideration of this point, then ſhould not ſo many ſymonaicall
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:184215:63"/>and vnworthy worldlings be preſented and admitted, nor ſo many godly and painefull paſtors be diſmiſſed as ther are, to the great woe and ſorrowe of many poore ſoules that haue receiued moſt ſweete comfort from their bleſſed miniſterie and painefull ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours in the Lord.</p>
            <p>But now it is time to enter combate and encounter with our aduerſaries the Papiſts: nay the aduerſaries of Chriſt and his church about this point, who wold beare the world in hand, that Ignorance is the mother of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, and that there is no neceſsitie of the ſcriptures for the common people, but that euery one muſt beleeue as the church belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth without any further triall or examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had of the matter by the word of God. Which bloudy doctrine, and vncomfortable aſſertion we ſhall ſee (by Gods grace) to fall downe and breake his necke at the ſight of the trueth, as <hi>Dagon</hi> the idoll of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes did at the preſence of the Arke.</p>
            <p>Ignorance (ſay the Papiſts) is the mother of Deuotion. And Ignorance (ſay the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) is the mother of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. Now ther is great oddes between Deuotion and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; as much as is betweene ignorance and knowledge, or between light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Indeede of Popiſh deuotion, whoſe fruites are idolatrie, and ſuperſtition, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:184215:64"/>and blaſphemie, and pride, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and couetouſneſſe, and treaſon, and all abhominations, and in the ende, eternall damnation. Ignoraunce is the mother, but not of true deuotion which pleaſeth God. Knowledge and Ignorance be contrarie one to another; and as they be contrarie cauſes; ſo their effects muſt needes be contrary, and that by the rule of contraries; for, <hi>Contrario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum contraria eſt ratio.</hi> Now if knowledge be the roote of faith, and of loue, and of zeale, and of obedience, and of all vertue and goodneſſe, as it is then is not ignorance the roote of faith, but of vnbeleefe, not of loue, but of hatred, not of zeale, but of raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and coldneſſe, not of obedience, but of rebellion, not of goodneſſe, but of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; and therefore not of deuotion ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but of damnation.</p>
            <p>In the ninetie fiue Pſalme the Lorde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth the Iewes of hardnes of heart, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God, and continuall rebellion againſt the Lorde for the ſpace of fortie yeeres, and addeth this withall as a reaſon of all their wickedneſſe, that they knew not the waies of the Lorde; for which cauſe, the Lorde ſware in his wrath, that they ſhoulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enter into his reſt, to ſhew vs what bee the fruites of ignoraunce; which if it bee the mother of deuotion, it is of ſuch deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:184215:64"/>as bringeth foorth all manner of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and ſhutteth men out of eternall fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</p>
            <p>In the fourth Chapiter of the Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> in the firſt, ſecond, third and fourth verſes, the Lord hath a controuerſy with the inhabitants of Iſrael, becauſe there was no trueth; nor mercie, nor knowledge of God amongſt them, but ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and whoring, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, for which things the Lord telleth them that the land ſhall mourne, and euerie one ſhall be cut off, to ſhew what is to bee looked for where the knowledge of God is wanting.</p>
            <p>When the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> reproued the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites idolatrie, and hypocriſie, hee ſaide; Knoweſt thou nothing? as if he ſhould ſay; theſe are the fruits of ignorance. In <hi>Philip.</hi> the firſt chapter and the ninth verſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle prayeth God, that the church might abound in knowledge and iudgement, which hee woulde not haue doone, if ignoraunce were the mother of deuotion. Our Sauiour Chriſt commaundeth his church to ſearch the Scriptures, adding this as a reaſon, that they beare witneſſe of him,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.39.</note> and ſhewe the way to eternall life, to ſhew that ignorance is not the mother of deuotion. By this may we ſee how much we are beholding to the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:184215:65"/>papiſts for ſhutting vp the doores of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge againſt the church of God. They are like the Philiſtines that put out the eies of Sampſon,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 16.21.</note> that ſo they might the better make ſport with him, and when the Papiſts had put out the right eye of knowledge in the church, they might then make them doe what they liſt themſelues. They are like the cruell <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the Ammonite that would make no couenaunt with the Iſraelites,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 11.2.</note> but vppon condition that euerie man woulde put out his right eye. The rauen when hee falleth vppon a ſheepe, the firſt thing hee doth, is to picke out his eies, that ſo he may the more eaſily deuoure the body; ſo when the Papiſts fall vpon the ſheepe of Chriſt, the firſt thing they labour to effect, is to put out their eies of knowledge, that ſo they may the more eaſily prey vpon their bodie and goodes too. They tell vs forſooth that the ſearching of the ſcripture is the cauſe of errour. And our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you erre becauſe you knowe not the ſcriptures,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12.24.</note> which of theſe muſt we beleeue, the Papiſts or our Sauiour Chriſt? They tel vs that the ſcriptures are hard to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, but the Lorde ſaith. Al the words of my mouth are righteous, there is no lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 8, 8, 9.</note> nor frowardneſſe in them. They are all plaine to him that will vnderſtand, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:184215:65"/>ſtraight, to them that would find knowledge. The papiſts ſay, they are hard, and the Lord ſaith, they are plaine and ſtraight; which of theſe now ſhal we beleeue, the papiſts, or the Lord? Indeede ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that in the writings of his brother <hi>Paul,</hi> there are ſome things hard to be vnderſtoode,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.1, 6</note> which igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt and vnſtable men doe peruert as they doe all other ſcriptures to their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: now if they be hard, we ſee to whome they are hard, to the ignorant and vnſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but not to thoſe that deſire knowledge, to them they are made eaſie by the Lorde. Therefore it muſt ſtand vs in hande to bee well repaired, and ſanctified by fayth and prayer, when wee deale with the ſcriptures, and bee truely reſolued to bee reformed thereby, or elſe wee may fall into errour, as a iuſt recompence of our pride &amp; preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<note place="margin">Exo. 19.</note> VVhen the Iſraelites ſhoulde come before the Lord, they muſt be ſanctified to day and to morrow ſaith the Lord: when we come to the handling of the ſcriptures, wee come before the Lorde, and therefore wee muſt bee throughly ſanctified, and with <hi>Moſes,</hi> wee muſt put off the ſhooes of our carnall affections when wee come to deale with the booke of GOD, for the ſcriptures are the mount, from which God doth ſhew himſelfe, and the buſh out of which goeth
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:184215:66"/>a flame of fire. In them the Lord ſpeaketh to vs, and wee heare the words of euerlaſting life, wee muſt therefore ſtrip off all our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and fall downe before the Lorde with feare, and knowe who it is that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. His worde is holy, let vs take heede therefore into what hearts we put it; wee may not receiue it to puffe vp our hearts, &amp; to waxe proud with knowledge, we may not vſe it to maintaine debate, and contention, to vaunt our ſelues, or to make ſhew of our cunning. His worde teacheth lowlineſſe of mind to know our ſelues. If wee learne not humility we learne nothing. The ſcriptures are Gods myſteries, therefore bee not too curious: they are Gods ſea, therefore take heede that wee bee not drowned in them. They are Gods fire, therefore take we heed that wee bee not burned in them. They are the glorious ſunne of the Lorde, to giue light to them that ſit in darkeneſſe and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, but they that gaze ouer hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vppon the ſunne, take blemiſh in their eie ſight. Now if wee come to the worde of God with that feare. and reuerence, &amp; paier, and faith, and repentance, and loue, &amp; zeale, and humilitie that ſhould be in vs, wee ſhall eaſily proue the papiſts liars, in ſaying the ſcriptures are hard, &amp; aboue the reach of the people, as <hi>Iulian</hi> the heretike ſaide, whom
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:184215:66"/>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> therefore reproueth verie ſharpely in writing againſt him.
<note place="margin">Auguſt. li. 5. Ca. 1. cont. Iuli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And great reaſon had hee for it, for God himſelf telles vs otherwiſe. In <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> chapter 30. 11, 12, 13, 14. verſes he ſaith. <hi>This comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement which I giue thee this day, is not hidden from thee, neither is it farre off. It is not in heauen, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, who ſhall goe vp for vs to heauen, and bring it vs, and cauſe vs to heare it, that woe may dooe it? Neither is it beyonde the Sea, that thou ſhouldeſt ſaie, who ſhall goe ouer the ſea for vs, and bring it vs, and cauſe vs to heare it, that wee may doe it? But the worde is very neare vnto thee, euen in thy mouth, and in thy heart for to do it.</hi> And in the nineteenth Pſalme he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pſalme. 19 7.</note> 
               <hi>that the law of the Lord is perfect, conuerting the ſoule, the teſtimonie of the Lorde is ſure, and giueth wiſedome vnto the ſimple, the ſtatutes of the Lorde are right, and reioyce the heart, the commaundement of the Lorde is pure, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth light vnto the eies: Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>The word of the Lorde is a lanterne vnto his feete,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.108.</note> 
               <hi>and a light vnto his pathes,</hi> and hee and wee muſt goe all by one light. Nowe if the light bee darke, then what is cleare? or what can hee ſee that cannot ſee the light. It is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent (ſayth a reuerend and learned Father,) that ſomething ſhoulde be couered to make vs more diligent in reading, more deſirous
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:184215:67"/>to vnderſtand,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell.</note> more feruent in prayer, more willing to aske the iudgement of others, and to preſume the leſſſe vppon our owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It cauſeth a man to take that profit by paines, which he could not take by negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. And al things (ſaith he) are plaine to him that hath ſound knowledge, but to fools the moſt eaſie places ſeeme hard; for how can wiſedome enter into a fooles heart, or a wicked mans heart, both which are enemies vnto wiſedome? They are like the Owle that cannot ſee the brightneſſe of the ſunne, not becauſe the ſunne beames are darke, but becauſe his eies are weake, and cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide ſo cleare a light.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctio.</note> But the Papiſts tel vs that they are not for the common people,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſio.</note> as though forſooth the common people were none of gods people, or had no ſouls to ſaue. The ſcriptures bee bread and drinke which nouriſheth vnto euerlaſting life, (ſaith the ſame father) &amp; great cruelty it is (ſaith he) to ſtarue Gods people to death; But what, are they vnfit to haue the ſcripturs becauſe they bee poore? why Chriſt ſaith, the poore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the goſpell,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 11.5.</note> and bleſſed are the poore in ſpirit, for theirs is the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.3</note> if the kingdome of heauen bee theirs, why ſhoulde they not haue the ſcriptures, as their euidence to ſhewe for the ſaide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance? What then? Are they vnfit to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:184215:67"/>haue the ſcriptures, becauſe they are vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? why the apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.2.</note> I eſteem to know nothing but Chriſt, and him crucified: &amp; our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith, that his father hath hid theſe things from the wiſe &amp; learned of the world, and reuealed them vnto babes, and ſimple ones. And the Apoſtles were ſent to all creatures, learned, and vnlearned, poore, and rich. There is none too poore, nor too rich, nor too olde, nor too yong, but whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath eare to heare hath learning inough to be a hearer. The wiſeſt, and the learned men in matters of this worlde, haue not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies prooued the readieſt to ſet forth the glory of God; for who reſiſted <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron?</hi> not the people, but the king &amp; the chief of Egypt. Who ſtoode againſt <hi>Elias,</hi> but the prieſts of <hi>Baal?</hi> who ſtoned the prophets, but the wiſeſt in Iſrael? who crucified Chriſt, but the Scribes and Phariſees, not the common people? wherein wee may ſee that fulfilled which the apoſtle alleadged out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſpeaking in the perſon of God,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.19,</note> I <hi>will deſtroy the wiſedome of the wiſe, and wil caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of the prudent;</hi> where is the wiſe? where is the ſcribe? where is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputer of this world? hath not God made the wiſedom of this world fooliſhnes? for ſeeing that the world by wiſedome knew not God in the wiſedome of God, it pleaſed God by
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:184215:68"/>the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue thoſe that beleeue, whether they be poore or rich, learned or vnlearned, that is no matter, ſo they beleeue they ſhall be ſaued, by the means of preaching, which by the wiſedom of the world is condemned for fooliſhneſſe. And thus we ſee the Papiſts condemned of moſt horrible crueltie and murther, for that they woulde of their chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie ſtarue Gods church, by withholding the food of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtanding from them.</p>
            <p>It is further to be obſerued, that thoſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors are promiſed of the Lord to come as a gift, both to ſhew how vnworthy wee are of ſuch a bleſsing, as alſo to teach vs how tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully we ſhould receiue it at the hands of the Lord that is the giuer. <hi>I wil giue you paſtors, &amp;c.</hi> as if he ſhould ſay; when you haue them you muſt not take them as due vnto you for your deſeruings (for you deſerue no good thing of me) but I will freely beſtowe them vpon my church. Amongſt temporal bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites there is none like a good wife: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſpiritual benefits there is none like a good paſtor: And both are ſent from God, to thoſe that feare him with this poſie vpon them, <hi>donum Dei,</hi> the gift of God; that if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould aske, Who giueth this woman to be married to this man? the Lord doth reach his hand as is were from heauen, ſaying, that
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:184215:68"/>do I; ſo if any man aske, who gaue this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour to this congregation? and other ſuch to the reſt of his church; the Lord doth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere from heauen and ſaith, that do I: he is my gift. And to thoſe that turne vnto me, I will giue paſtours according to my heart; <hi>for houſe and riches are the inheritance of the fathers,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, but a prudent wife com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of the Lord Pr.</hi> 19 14. So a good paſtor comes not as houſe and land, by inheritance, but as a good wife comes, and that is of the Lord. Such paſtours and teachers are ſent as ſpeciall loue tokens to the godly, whereby they may knowe how the Lorde doth loue them. But ignorant miniſters, and Non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents, and time-ſeruers, &amp; idoll ſhepherds, and ſuch like are ſent of God to the wicked. as <hi>Saul</hi> was giuen to Iſraell in his wrath to plague them withal, and to ſtrengthen them in their ſinnes, and ſo to ſeale vp their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of a harlot;
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 22</note> 
               <hi>The lippes of a ſtrange woman are as a deep pit and he with whom the Lord is angrie ſhall fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame;</hi> ſo may it be ſaide of wicked pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and blinde guides, they and their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple goe together into the ditch, and they whome the Lord is angrie with, ſhal be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued with ſuch. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt aſcending vp on high gaue gifts vnto men, ſome to be apoſtles, ſome to be
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:184215:69"/>paſtours and doctors, &amp;c. and thoſe he gaue to his church, for the gathering together his ſaints, to teach vs that they are not ſent of God like marchandiſe for our money (as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Magus</hi> thought of the gifts of the holie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghoſt) but they are ſent as gifts,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 20.</note> and are to be receiued as the gifts of the Lord. The only way to obtaine ſuch gifts,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 9.37, 38.</note> is by prayer, <hi>The harueſt is great</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are few, pray ye therefore to the Lorde of the harueſt, and he ſhall ſend foorth labourers,</hi> to ſhew that God will haue his giftes dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen from him by prayer, that is, he vell be knowen and acknowledged to be the giuer of them, as men will ſay, if hee had asked it of me, I would haue giuen it him; ſo doth the Lord ſay; if they had asked ſuch paſtors of me, I would haue giuen them ſuch. This therefore is the cauſe why there are ſo fewe true labourers in the Lordes harueſt, and ſo many wicked loiterers, becauſe the church in generall, and congregations, and chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in particular, are not earneſt enough in prayer vnto God for them; for (as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith) <hi>We ſhould not giue the Lorde any reſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>but, as it were, wearie him with our prayers, vntill he repaire the decayed places of Zion, and build vp Ieruſalem in her perfect beautie, which is the praiſe of the worlde:</hi> Neither are good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors gotten, nor bad ones diſplaced, by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:184215:69"/>and libelling againſt Biſhops, and the gouernours of the church, (as ſome haue thought) nor by factious and ſeditious draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of multitudes to practiſe againſt the ſworde of authoritie, nor by robbing the church of her children, nor by ſciſmaticall ſeperating of our ſelues from the church, as hereticall ſchiſmatikes doe thinke, nor by withdrawing of their liuings as couetous worldlings imagin, but by humble ſuing to God with prayer and ſupplications, for ſo are his gifts obtained; ſo that if men woulde leaue their ſcurrilous libelling, and their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely railing, and their vaine talking, and their ſciſmaticall ſeperating, and their ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious banding, and their cruell dealing, and now another while trie the Lord by turning vnto him, as here he requireth vs, and plie him with our humble prayers, as Chriſt hath commaunded vs, there is no doubt, but it would goe better with the poore church of Chriſt then it doth; for if we do that which is required of vs, moſt certainely the Lorde will performe that which hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Nowe where the Lord hath beſtowed ſuch paſtors, and planted the meanes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, there is much (no doubt) required againe.
<note place="margin">What is requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of them that haue good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours.</note> Two things doth the Lord expect and looke for at their hands which haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſuch gifts of the Lorde; namely, loue
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:184215:70"/>and obedience: for loue requires loue again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſeeing theſe gifts are ſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord as ſpecial tokens of his loue &amp; fauor toward vs, his maieſtie lookes for great loue again of vs towards the gift for his ſake that gaue it, &amp; towards the giuer for his own goodnes ſake, which only moued him to giue the gift. And ſith he giueth them to feede vs with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; vnderſtanding, he laboreth that we ſhould grow and thriue therby, that is, to be the better reformed, both in iudgements &amp; alſo in our maners. But that it may appeare the better what loue we owe to the Lord in this reſpect, we ought to conſider the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, goodnes, &amp; value of the gift, wherby we ſhal al ſee the great loue and goodnes of him that is the giuer. <hi>Euery man is friend vnto him that giueth gifts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orerb. 19.6.</note> then euery man ſhould loue the Lord, for none giueth ſo many gifts as he doth; yea for the gifts which men giue, the Lord is to be loued, bicauſe they had neither what to giue, nor wil to giue, vntill the Lord giue both. Al the gifts of the Lord are either bodily or ſpiritual, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral or eternal, general or ſpecial; ſome are common to man &amp; beaſt &amp; ſome are common to good and bad, to the reprobate &amp; the elect, as meate, &amp; drinke &amp; apparel, appetite and digeſtion, houſes and lands, cattel and corne, gold &amp; ſiluer, health and welth, wife &amp; children, beuty &amp; honor,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:184215:70"/>peace and plenty, learning and wit, wiſdom and policy, frends and promotion, and many ſuch like, the leaſt wherof deſerueth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that wee ſhoulde loue and feare the Lord with al our harts, with al our ſtrength: but beſides theſe, the daily giftes which the Lord giueth to man, and to the earth, &amp; the ſea, and the heauens; yea the whole world for mans vſe they are infinit, that to go about to nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber them, were to meaſure the ſea with a ſpoon; for which we return nothing but our ſins, which are mo then his benefits: yet ſuch is his goodnes that giueth al, &amp; forgiueth al. But amongſt al the Lords gifts, there is none comparable to paſtors that feed mens ſoules with knoledge &amp; vnderſtanding. When <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> would ſet out the greatnes of this gift, he reherſeth many works of god ſhewed in his church, for which he is to be praiſed;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.13, 1</note> 
               <hi>Praiſe the Lord, O Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, praiſe thy God O Zion, for he hath made the bars of thy gates ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; hath bleſsed thy children within thee,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
               <hi>he ſetteth peace in thy borders, &amp; ſatisfieth thee with the flour of wheat.</hi> When he conſidereth the benefit of Gods word, he ſaith; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> 
               <hi>He ſheweth his word vnto Iacob, his ſtatutes and iudgements vnto Iſrael: he hath not dealt ſo with euery nation;</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> to ſhew that the word of God is a ſpeciall bleſsing, and not to be reckoned amongſt ſuch things as are common to all nations of the world.</p>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:184215:71"/>
            <p> When the Apoſtle ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> would ſet out the greatneſſe of this gift,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he ſaith, that <hi>the grace of God which bringeth ſaluation hath appeared,</hi> meaning the goſpel, to ſhew that men cannot be ſaued without it; ſo great, ſo good, ſo excellent, and ſo neceſſarie it is. All other bleſsings are of the grace of God; there is an enriching grace, a healthy grace, and a wealthy grace, and a healing grace, &amp;c. But this is called the ſauing grace of GOD. <hi>Dauid</hi> preferreth it before his kingdome, becauſe it did comfort him in his affliction; <hi>if thy word</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>had not beene my comfort in my affliction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 119.92.</note> 
               <hi>I had periſhed,</hi> to ſhew that the word of God is better then a kingdome. This may make the children of God the more to loue ſuch meſſengers, as bring ſuch tidings of peace, and to feare ſuch a God, as giueth ſuch gifts vnto men; but as for the wicked whoſe eies the god of this worlde, that is, Sathan, hath blinded, to them it is but as a tale of a fooliſh thing, for they are like the ſwine, which finde more ſauour in the mire, then in ſweet perfumes; or like the dunghil cocke, that had rather find a graine of corne, then a precious ſtone. If ſweete floures be giuen to him that hath his ſences, they will ſmell ſweete, but a dead man feeles no ſweetneſſe in them, though they be put to his noſe; ſo the ſpirituall and regenerate
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:184215:71"/>man ſhall feele the ſweetnes and goodnes of this gift, but the carnall man, in whome is not the life of the ſpirite, ſhall neuer make any account of it. Againe, the faithfull doe not onely loue the giuer for his gift, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo maketh much of the gift, for the giuers ſake; as men will ſay of their friends giftes or tokens, I will not part withall, I wil keep it full daintily (though they haue no vſe for it) for his ſake that beſtowed it on me: much more doe the faithfull reuerence the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and their paſtours which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour amongeſt them in word and doctrine, and are ouer them in the Lord; they make much of them, yea they haue them in ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar account for their workes ſake, and keepe them very carefully, both becauſe the Lord gaue them, and they haue a maruelous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and heauenly vſe of them to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſaluation. Whereas the wicked who neuer knew the worth or want of good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, nor the neceſsitie of knowledge and vnderſtanding, doe they take them to bee ſent of God as tokens of his loue, or as the onely meanes of ſaluation, or doe they feare the Lord euer the more for ſuch gifts? or do they loue and reuerence the gifts for the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſake? or doe they account of them for their ſake? No, no ſuch matter, they knowe not what theſe things mean, they take them
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:184215:72"/>rather for their enimies,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng. 21.20.</note> as <hi>Achab</hi> did <hi>Eliah</hi> who ſaid, haſt thou found me O my enimy? they take them as men ſent of the Lorde, or rather come out from the deuill to plague them,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ouble them, as <hi>Herod</hi> and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem thought of Chriſt: and after that rate doe they vſe them, with all reproches and mockes that can be deuiſed, with al diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, with all manner of iniuries and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and thus doe the wicked rewarde their paſtours which feede them, which they woulde not doe, if they did take them as the gifts of God: but al this ought not to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage paſtours and preachers of the worde, becauſe baſe perſons doe baſely account of them, but rather confirme them in the ſaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full execution of their office, taking the hatred of the worlde as a ſure token of their miniſters effectuall working, and let them learne to play the parte of a nurſe with their people, who hath manie a foule hande with the childe before ſhee can bring it to anie perfection. And let them bee content to become like torches, which burne out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues while they giue light vnto others, not feareing the faces of men becauſe the Lorde is a braſen wall betweene them and their aduerſaries, and though they bee ill rewarded of the worlde, yet let them bee glad, for as much as they looke for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:184215:72"/>from the lord who hath ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a worke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I wil giue.]</hi> The laſt thing we haue to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue here, is, that the Lord doth not onely ſay you ſhall haue paſtors, but <hi>I will giue you paſtours according to my heart:</hi> if his people will repent, hee will performe that which is promiſed &amp; none other for him; this is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the churches faith, when the lord himſelf doth promiſe a thing, &amp; vndertake the performance of it himſelfe. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had made ſuch a promiſe the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance remaineth doubtful, becauſe he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toth power, or skil, or conſtancie, his minde may alter, or meanes may faile, or hee may bee croſſed with ſome higher power; but with the Lorde is no ſuch thing, for he hath both power and skil, and is alwaies the ſame and changeth not, neither is there any power aboue him to croſſe his maieſtie. If an angell from heauen had made ſuch a promiſe, yet the performance is doutful, becauſe he is but a creature, &amp; is ſubiect to the checke, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolement of the Lord; but if god ſay he wil, it ſhalbe, as the Centurion ſaid,
<note place="margin">Luke. 7.7</note> 
               <hi>Lorde doe but ſpeak the word &amp; my ſeruant ſhalbe whole;</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power &amp; wil of god do meete, then there wants nothing to let the matter, but our ſins, <hi>Lord if thou wilt</hi> (ſaith the leaper) <hi>thou canſt make me eleane. I will</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>be thou cleane, and immediatly the leproſie was cleanſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:184215:73"/>
            <p> But this people were in captiuitie,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.3.</note> &amp; their enemies had dominion ouer them: how wil the Lord reſtore them? very wel; for the lord is able to do it either by force of angels, as he deliuered <hi>Peter</hi> out of priſon, or by men, or by other creatures, as he delt with <hi>Pharao,</hi> or by turning their enimies hearts, as he turned <hi>Saules</hi> heart, when he followed <hi>Dauid</hi> to kil him,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns 24.18.</note> according to the ſaying of <hi>Salomon. When a mans waies pleaſe the Lorde, hee will cauſe his foes to become his friends,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.7.</note> or without meanes, onely by that worde, whereby hee made heauen and earth and all the worlde,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</note> when matter was wanting. Hereof we haue many examples: God ſaid he woulde make Iſrael a mightie people,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.10.</note> could <hi>Pharao</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it? no, though hee ſaid, <hi>Come and let vs worke wiſely with them, leſt they multiply &amp;c.</hi> God ſaid <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhould be king, could <hi>Saule</hi> preuent it? no, though he ſaid, I wil giue him my eldeſt daughter vppon condition that he bring mee a hundred foreskins of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 18.17, 25.</note> thinking by this pollicy to make a rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of him. God ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſhal raigne, could any defeat her? no, though firſt they ſifted her for treaſon, as conſpiring with <hi>Wiat,</hi> and then <hi>Gardiner</hi> the wolfe cried ſtil, ſtub vppe the roote, ſtub vp the roote: then how many waies haue beene deuiſed ſince to ſubuert her by papiſts, and traitours, and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:184215:73"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſuites, and the vnholy league, and all with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he deuill himſelfe, hauing ſworne &amp; vowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdeath; yet ſhe raigneth, thanked be God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd long may ſhe raigne O Lord we bſeech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee for thy mercies ſake, in deſpite of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y enemies: here we may ſee that verefied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is in the Prouerbs, <hi>There is no counſaile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or wiſedome, nor ſtrength, againſt the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19.21.</note> And in another place he ſaith, <hi>Many deuiſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re in a mans heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.25.</note> 
               <hi>but the counſell of the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all ſtand.</hi> If any thing hinder good things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom vs, it is our ſinne, but no deuiſe of man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or deuill, they ſhall doe no more then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orde hath appointed. Our ſinnes are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hiefe cauſe, and the wicked are inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all cauſes, and vſed by the Lord like <hi>Aſhur,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>who was called the ſtaffe of the Lord) to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lague his church withall. And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any take a wrong courſe to haue the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes eſtate bettered, they crie out vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me, and the ſtate, and the Biſhops, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ons, and the dumbe miniſters (I ſpeake not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow in defence of any mans fault or corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on) but their owne houſehold are vnrefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, they and their families are ignorant and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rofane, they abuſe the good gifts of god al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eady beſtowed, and yet they find fault they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue no more, like children that caſt their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eate to the dogges and then crie for more: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſay, ſo long as ſuch and ſuch beare ſway
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:184215:74"/>in the church, neuer a good miniſter ſhal be long at reſt, and I know not what, neuer loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king what hurt their raſhnes and prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous blind zeale doth procure: but they are much deceiued, for let thoſe that call vppon the name of God departe from euill, and turne vnto the Lorde, and then looke what his maieſtie hath promiſed, it ſhall ſurely be performed, though the time be prolonged for the exerciſe of our faith, &amp; patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. It is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs, if the Lord ſaith he wil do it, though he do not tell vs when, and howe he will do it, hee hath wayes enow to bring his counſel to paſſe. With this <hi>[I wil]</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God let vs learne to arme our ſelues againſt all temptations, all feares, all doubts, and all lets whatſoeuer, let men take heede how they enterpriſe any thing againſt the will of God, what meanes ſoeuer they haue to effect their purpoſe, for if they ſay, they will, and the Lord ſay, hee wil not, or if they ſay, it ſhal not be, and the Lord ſaith, it ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be, all their murmuring &amp; banding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſac. 36.12. and 37.33.</note> and practiſing will be in vaine; <hi>Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charib</hi> ſaid he would come againſt Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem with a mightie hoſt, and make them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eate their owne dunge and drinke their ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> piſſe, but the Lord ſaid he ſhould not ſhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an arrow into Ieruſalem, and it came to paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the Lord ſaid. <hi>Eſau</hi> ſaid hee would kill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:184215:74"/>brother <hi>Iacob,</hi> but he did not,
<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Iewes vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neither to eate nor drinke till they hadde killed <hi>Paule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 21.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but if they had kept their vowe they had ſtarued. <hi>Herod</hi> though to haue kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſt, but hee coulde not, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue purpoſed many other things, but the Lord hath diſpoſed of them according to his own wil and pleaſure; and all to ſhewe how truely <hi>Iob</hi> ſpake when he ſaid, <hi>The hand of man is not able to accompliſh the deuiſe of his heart.</hi> As this is a ſingular conſolation at all times, ſo now in this hard time of dearth and ſcarcitie, the Lord doth promiſe vppon the true repentance of his people, to bleſſe the earth, with plentie, &amp; to ſatifie the poore with bread, let the wretched cornemongers, and couetous caterpillers ſay, the price ſhall not fall, the Lord that hath ſaid the word wil do it manger their beards, and cauſe them to fall too, with ſhame inough if they repent not: let no man ſay as the noble man of <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> ſaid,
<note place="margin">2. King. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Though the Lord ſhould open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heauen and raine downe wheate, &amp;c.</hi> I will not beleeue the words of the prophet, leſt he ſee it, but enioy it, not as hee did that was troden downe in the gates of the cittie. And to conclude, ſeeing as we are readie to take a mans word for any thing, if hee be an honeſt man, and of any credit or ability, and think our ſelues ſafe, if the prince, or a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:184215:75"/>perſon ſay; I will giue thee this or tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> how much more ought we to take the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> word for any thing that he promiſeth, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is all ſufficient and faithfull? yea if wee do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doubt of the matter when he ſaith, I will, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſume when hee ſaith, I wil not, wee offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his maieſtie that iniurie, which we our ſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would hardly let go vnreuenged at any mans hand, if it lay in our power to reuenge the ſame.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:184215:75"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
